Introduction

Are you angry at the craziness going on in U.S. politics?  Are you frustrated that the United States Congress lacks a backbone and couldn't crawl it's way out of an open paper bag lying on its side?  Do you fear economic hard times, more school shootings, and overpriced access to kitten videos?

This is the entertaining comic story of a young man named Damien and a young woman named Desha who together dig under many layers of political dung and entertaining distractions to uncover the secret tactic that wealthy business owners use to control politicians in both the Republican and Democratic parties.

Even better, Damien and Desha learn the solution that eventually will reduce corruption in politics.  The name of the solution is simple.  It's called pairwise counting.  What does this mean?  Read the story to join Damien and Desha in their insightful adventure!

This book is a comedy, written entirely in dialog.  Soon this dialog will be performed by voice actors to create an audiobook.  Later there will be a video version.  To find out more about the audiobook and any video versions, point your browser to: SolutionsCreative.com  In the meantime, please learn the secret explained in this book, and then tell your friends.

The author also explains this secret in his book titled Ending The Hidden Unfairness In U.S. Elections.  But that non-fiction book is, for most people, too dry (not as entertaining) and too long.  Here you can have fun as you learn the secret you will want to share with your friends.

Characters

Damien, D: Male, tenor voice.

Katerina, K: Female, soprano or alto voice.

Jordon, J: Male, baritone voice.

Fred Finckster, F: Male (or possibly female), tenor voice.

Desha, De: Female, alto voice.

Mata, M: Female (or possibly male), soprano or maybe alto voice.

Pengaritihas, P: Male (or possibly female), tenor voice.

Whit, W: Male, tenor voice.

Grafton, G: Male, bass or baritone voice.

Additional characteristics are revealed in the dialog.

Scene 1, Our Middle Class Dreams

Katerina: Damien! Are you thinking of jumping off?

Damien: With today's luck I'd land on something soft.

Katerina: Like a truckload of pumpkins? Or a cart of dung?

Damien: Or my head.

Katerina: That would put a dent in paying next month's rent. What's the matter?

Damien: I'm (slurred first word) feelin' sadder than a dolphin with no fin.

Katerina: Named Adolf? Why so abysmal?

Damien: Life is so unfair. My dream's been shattered.

Katerina: Which dream's been fractured? The picket fence around a front yard that's big enough for a Saint Bernard?

Damien: That's your dream. Mine was to enter the middle class.

Katerina: Yeah, to gain that entrance you've been bustin' your ass.

Damien: My butt is busted. What more does it take?

Katerina: Maybe a secret handshake?

Damien: Today my boss popped my bubble.

Katerina: Is his business in trouble?

Damien: Nah, but he told me some stuff, about some laws that are rough.

Katerina: The ones corporations can avoid?

Damien: Yeah, that's got me annoyed.

Katerina: Some corporations are more corrupt than those long-ago traveling medicine shows.

Damien: And us taxpayers get pushed to the edge. We're looking down into a volcano of molten lava called bankruptcy.

Katerina: You didn't tell me we're close to the edge. How can this be?

Damien: How is it that we who vote are not the ones keeping afloat? We're supposed to have democracy!

Katerina: Yes we can vote, but most candidates are wimpy puppets, or con artists, or can't-win third-party whiners.

Damien: Marking the ballot oval for any such fink tickles my nose with a sulferous stink.

Katerina: Yeah it's a big kink in democracy.

Damien: How can this be?

Katerina: It does seem crazy. Laws always favor the wealthy.

Damien: Yet they are fewer in number than rabbits behind the path of a coyote pack.

Katerina: And there are so many of us, making a big fuss.

Damien: How can the rich outvote us? Is the only prognosis hopelessness?

Katerina: Maybe it's hypnosis? Or the political ads I suppose.

Damien: We can see through those. Something's hidden. There's got to be another villian.

Katerina: A conspiracy? A dark-money tyranny? Or a Bermuda pentagon with two sides missing?

Damien: I don't know. But as my dad would say, "Get to the root of the problem, that's where the solution lay."

Katerina: My parents, they taught me, suit up, show up, pay attention, and then pretend to work work work.

Damien: Willing to bust my ass, that I'm willin' to do. But not if we're following the footsteps of Native Americans.

Katerina: Footsteps?

Damien: They said "The white man are like wolves who herd us like buffalo from our grazing lands onto deserts. They take our lands to fuel their greed beyond their need."

Katerina: We're being herded. Something's not right.

Damien: Damn I want to know whose hand I should bite!

Katerina: Financially, our life is so far upside down from where I want it to be.

Damien: I wanna be an employer, but I'm just an employee.

Katerina: I wanna be a princess. But do you see a tiara on my empty head?

Damien: We're upside down. It's not our nose that should run. It's our feet that should run.

Katerina: It's not our feet that should smell. It's our nose that should smell.

Damien: We're upside down. Our finances are in the red, not in the black.

Katerina: If the look of our teeth gives us good cheer, at dinner out with friends we can't afford beer.

Damien: If our dinner plate has roasted veggies and some meat, then our car's gas gauge says stay at home this weekend.

Katerina: Do you want a chocolate truffle?

Damien: Something brown to get me down, no thanks.

Katerina: They're delicious.

Damien: I'm suspicious. Something's going on behind our backs.

Katerina: Yes, right in front of our eyes. The trickle-down economy works for corporations, but not for us.

Damien: Work and cash should come as a pair, but one without the other, that's not fair!

Katerina: We're stuck doing dull work for bosses that are jerks.

Damien: The boss I've got is a saint compared to others. But now he says he's drowning. There's taxes and licenses, and insurance, and yet more fees. Just keeping track of these adds another employee.

Katerina: That leaves less money for us.

Damien: I know how to invent but that don't pay the rent. Not yet. And it won't if I can't figure out how to own my own business.

Katerina: I've read that suicide is done by men who can't find anyone else to blame. So who is rigging the political game?

Damien: I don't know. Politics is so complex.

Katerina: Yeah, everything interconnects.

Damien: Yet surely somewhere, perhaps in disguise, are a few people who are wise.

Katerina: Even Google cannot track those needles in the global haystack.

Damien: 'Specially because online networks push us to the money-backed jerks.

Katerina: Yeah, the evil ones who take away from the top of our take-home pay. Let's say you found a guru who knew, what would you ask, specifically?

Damien: How can we get real democracy? Wait, I'll substitute. What's at the root of unfairness in business and the tactics used in politics?

Katerina: Bright professors teach at the local college. Probably in political science they teach about the electoral college and gerrymandation, er, German dating, or whatever, and the Constitution.

Damien: I'd rather walk into a rattlesnake cage than open another textbook. They shake my eyes more than the snake's tail. And my brain throbs as it tries to travel where weaselly words try to drag me. And tests, those devils just try to figure out if you read the textbook. Now that's a real conspiracy.

Katerina: I have to agree. Textbooks and tests are in it together.

Damien: Just being inside a classroom feels like I've stepped into a boxing ring wearing not boxing gloves but holding pom poms.

Katerina: Ah yes, community college classes already knocked you out for the count.

Damien: Does it matter? History is just about the past that's gone.

Katerina: Just like Elvis. I admit I don't remember much.

Damien: My math teacher said a monkey with a bad resume could have done better on his tests. And fractions were created by the devil!

Katerina: Alas you have to deal with evil fractions every day at work.

Damien: I cry inside when I get a measurement like thirteen and five sixteenths inches.

Katerina: I wouldn't know what to do with that.

Damien: Why should I struggle in the academic jungle?

Katerina: I admit I don't recall much at all from classes I took.

Damien: Anyway, do political scientists understand why politics is so upside down? With rich on top n' us voters mucking around in a financial swamp.

Katerina: I suppose you're right.

Damien: Who should I fight? What's the tipping point? How can we, the majority, outvote the slush funds of the rich elite?

Katerina: I'll ask father. He might know someone who knows those secrets.

Damien: I know I'm not the sharpest banana in the fruit basket. But if there should be a really sharp banana who can tell me, without pointing to some heavy book, why the world is so upside down, then I'll stuggle to learn those secrets.

Katerina: And when you find out who's to blame for corruption in government, what comes next?

Damien: Then I'll know how to earn the money we deserve. For working so hard for the masters we serve.

Katerina: If you don't figure this out, are you going to jump?

Damien: I won't jump. I'm not a chump. When the going gets tough, I'll jump back on the crocodile and keep on ridin'. 'Cause I'm dyin'. To know why things are upside down.

Katerina: As long as you're not dyin' on me.

Damien: Some people say this is just the way it will always be. But that's not OK for me. It isn't fair! Getting ahead. Rising to the top. Why does it seem to happen just for jerks and windbags?

Katerina: Yes, us hard workers deserve some perks too, don't we?

Damien: Seats in Congress should go to the wise.

Katerina: Yet the winners are selfish liars.

Damien: We voters want problem-solving leaders. But what do we get?

Katerina: Special-interest puppets who do the bidding of the wealthy few.

Damien: What do those puppet-masters get?

Katerina: Even richer!

Damien: And what do the rest of us get?

Katerina: Treated like a light bulb. Screwed!

Damien: I want to change the world and turn it right side up!

Katerina: The impossible. That's part of why I love you so. You want things to to be fair. You really care! But you'll need lots and lots of luck.

Damien: Yet with it I'll discover a way out of this muck.

Katerina: And then finally we can reach prosperity.

Damien: And suffer less adversity.

Katerina: I'll ask father for some help.

Damien: And I'll use my soft brain as a shovel to dig deep into the elephant and donkey dung! My sanity depends on it.

Scene 2, Money Madness

Damien: [Enters room while Jordon remains seated.] 'ello mister Morton. Grafton, m' fiance's father, said you make money dance. 'N I'd like to advance m' state of finance. Could ya teach me some tricks?

Jordon: Shall we start with some licks? In the fridge is some mint chocolate chip ice cream. Want some?

Damien: Tha's too rich a taste for me. Risin' out of serfdom. That's my dream. I wanna pass to th' middle class. I long t' be financially secure as an entrepreneur.

Jordon: I applaud your taste for money. Lots of folks are fond of stuffed bears, warm and fuzzy. But a wallet that's fat, just like me, what's better than that?

Damien: Withou' money my world feels upside down, like a turtle on it's back.

Jordon: With money, my world feels right side up. I've got a knack for earning lots of wealth. It's like getting payouts spilling onto the floor from a slot machine. Yet I want more. I can't afford my own jet, or a yacht. Not there yet. Don't yet got all I want.

Damien: S' what's th' trick? Of gettin' money to fund a life not wrecked.

Jordon: You've got to treat other people with respect, before you step on their toes. Then anything goes. That's the trick. That's how I behave like a ... an entrepreneur.

Damien: S' you put Benjamins before humans?

Jordon: Think about this. The love of money is built into our language. We have zillions of words for money. There's alimony, annuities, assets, bonds, and bonus, bounty, bribe, and capital, cash, and commodities, credit, currency, debit, discount, expense, and funds, income, interest, investment, options, pension, ransom, rebate, and remittance, rent, revenue, securities, shares, subsidy, and wage, and even those awful words like charity and donation.

Damien: 'N besides words for mula and dough, there're words like banker, accountant, miser, 'n vulture capitalist.

Jordon: And investor, and venture capitalist, which are what I am.

Damien: Yeah, money's damn importan'.

Jordon: Did you know that long ago, when writing was new, writing was used for banking 'n accounting?

Damien: Huh?

Jordon: That way money was stored in banks, not in pockets nor in bags anymore. That protected traders from pirates, thieves, and marauding desperados.

Damien: Ah, pirates. Tha' was a profession back when swashbuckling exams were open to th' poor.

Jordon: Pickpockets, pirates, and highway robbers are becoming as uncommon as blue-footed boobies. Now that money travels out of sight at the speed of light.

Damien: 'N th' modern version of pirates is lawyers?

Jordon: Oh no, today's lawyers are like ancient scribes.

Damien: S' how do you choose where to put th' money you've got, to get more?

Jordon: Besides side-stepping traps set by gold diggers, I only invest in high-profit deals.

Damien: Why not invest in businesses tha' offer value?

Jordon: The high-profit one has to compensate for the other eight, the deals that flop. Like Enron, America Online, and the early pets dot com.

Damien: S' you're seekin' th' one big standout you can brag about?

Jordon: Ah, yes, the unicorn. The one that swells my pockets til they burst. Missing out on one of those would be the worst. Yes, one unicorn in the forest is worth more than five zebras in the brush.

Damien: Zebras?

Jordon: Those are the small businesses that grow slow, by making and selling something of quality that consumers readily want. They don't need our venture capital for big marketing blitzes.

Damien: Isn't th' whole business scene about selling what customers want? 'R crave, like caffeine, nicotine, 'n Beanie Babies [chocolate covered almonds?]?

Jordon: Sure money can be used to undercut obstinate customer dissatisfaction.

Damien: What I mean is ideally I'd like to find fundin' for a business idea. I've invented a tool for cleanin' leaf gutters, withou' gettin' on a ladder. Would ya invest in a business that sells th' best kind of tool for that task?

Jordon: Nah, that's not much better than a cordless bungee-jumping franchise.

Damien: Lots o' people get injured, fallin' off a ladder while cleanin' gutters. Some land on their head, and end up dead.

Jordon: That's a great spin! Fear of falling. That's a fear that would sell lots of product. Do you have a patent?

Damien: I can't afford that cost. Tha's like thousands of dollars.

Jordon: Many tens of thousands of clams.

Damien: I couldn't afford even a few hundred dollars to ...

Jordon: Why would I invest unless there's a barrier against competition? There's gotta be a monopoly. Or some kind of virtual monopoly. That way my investment doesn't evaporate like a raindrop on a Detroit skyscraper's corner office window on a dry summer day.

Damien: So a workin' prototype's not enough?

Jordon: Nope. That's as useless as a machine-gun mount on the back of a golf cart. What the biz needs is a big amount of income, plus customers and testimonials. Then we'd invest.

Damien: If income I already had, I could self-fund it. 'N with that I could go to a bank 'n ask for a loan.

Jordon: Ha, the bank officials might nod ernestly. They might even encourage you to fill out forms. But when you've stepped out the door, they'll wet themselves with laughter.

Damien: If I were t' buy a house they'd loan for that.

Jordon: A mortgage, hah. It doesn't work like that. Instead the bank buys the house. Your down payment's big enough to cover a university education. So if you default after a few months, they sell the house, and you've bought a cap and gown and diploma for a banker's kid.

Damien: So banks don't loan money?

Jordon: They still do a bit, sometimes. Mostly now they're high-rolling gamblers that make casinos look like kids playing a game of Monopoly. They make big money by buying and selling, ah, another word for money, derivatives. Big things, not small things.

Damien: Wha' are derivatives?

Jordon: Those are contracts on paper, or the cyberspace equivalent, written by lawyers. Lots of times they're promises to pay money if something happens, like if interest rates rise or fall.

Damien: That sounds a lot like gamblin'.

Jordon: It is. And gambling, that's what we venture capitalists do too. We loan money. It's like those ancient sea voyages. Someone had to buy the ship and pay sailors before they could even set sail. Then, on return, if they returned, the cargo was sold, and the backer got his share of the profits.

Damien: 'N th' captain 'n crew got what?

Jordon: What they got was a temporary pass to the middle class. Until they got swindled, or beat at roulette, or divorced.

Damien: Bu' th' backer got more?

Jordon: Of course, 'cause he took the biggest risk.

Damien: Those times sound barbaric.

Jordon: They were. In those ancient times fighting was done by soldiers, and hard labor was done by workers. Now fighting is so much safer. It's done by lawyers fighting with legal documents instead of swords, and wearing colorful neckties instead of armour or bullet-proof vests. Whoever pays the most wins in court 'n gets the most. Quite civilized nowadays.

Damien: I think I see how money works. So how can I switch from bein' 'n employee to become an employer? Ownin' a small business, that's my dream. Some success, financially, so I c'n buy a fixer-upper house, pay for ultra-fast access to, er, ..., kitten videos, 'n drive a car that didn't come off Henry Ford's production line. Not a yacht, a cabin no, I jus' want fair rewards for my hard work. How do I take that leap?

Jordon: Leverage is the key. You need a vision. And you must find workers who follow you like ducklings follow their mom. You work them hard. You hire lawyers to sue any competitors. And of course you hire marketing folks who super-size your PR blitzes that get consumers to trust your brand.

Damien: S' I should start a cult? 'N of course there'd be 'n app with that.

Jordon: That might put you on the wealthy map. If you shift the idolotry to money.

Damien: 'T sounds like makin' money is about lyin' and cheatin'.

Jordon: It's not lying. That's not cheating. It's marketing and stepping on toes. In fact anything goes. But not lying and cheating. 'Cause that lands you in the slammer. That'd be a bummer 'cause your bank accounts can't protect you when you drop the bar of soap in the prison shower.

Damien: T' get ahead financially I have to step on people's toes?

Jordon: Or a gentle push to the nose. Business is all about competition. It's the very foundation of a free market.

Damien: Stomping on toes. Anything goes. That's th' trick of corporations. Why are they th' winners in th' business world?

Jordon: Ah the key is politics. We shareholders and investors give money to politicians. Then to us they listen. That's not cheating. It's not against any law. I share mula with any politician who passes laws that dump big amounts of golden coins into my bank accounts.

Damien: After your money buys you a louder voice, in politics, wha'dya get from th' politicians you buy?

Jordon: Tax breaks and subsidies. And sometimes legal monopolies. Oh I do love these. With these breaks, my business thrives.

Damien: But not so for others' lives. Th' customers. Th' employees.

Jordon: If someone else gets beaten, that's their choice. They need to speak up with a louder voice.

Damien: Don't you fear th' folks who want to tax th' wealthy?

Jordon: The business that I closely own, with more profit it could buy a Tesla SUV, or a ski lodge, or a yacht. Something I don't yet got. My biz buddies and I would share it. That tactic evades hefty income tax rates. So an extra tax on the rich, it misses me.

Damien: So th' key is ownin' a biz?

Jordon: Or getting on the board of directors. Three businesses pay me to travel to their board meetings. There we vote to reduce labor costs. Using bigger profits from the previous year's decisions, we vote for huge bonuses for ourselves. That's sandwiched within a resort vacation. At a fancy spot where I lounge for days with a date who's hot. Or at least I indulge in rich meals with a Flirty Felicity from Philly. Plus I do some side deals. And most of it's deductible, a money word that brings me joy.

Damien: So th' tax breaks and subsidies are for companies. Th' ones you own, or own shares of?

Jordon: Yup. The paperwork's a hassle, but those sly tricks are legal. All because we pay off politicians.

Damien: Don't lawyers also assist?

Jordon: Yes our lawyers fight battles in court. They exterminate our enemies. But nowadays no blood is shed. The loser only suffers financially.

Damien: It seems th' lawyers at th' top of th' legal food chain always win. Why's that?

Jordon: They write the bills that get passed into law. So of course they know where the loopholes are. It's all a big family. I do love it.

Damien: Is that all that money's needed for, to get those competitive edges?

Jordon: A way to cling to our riches is to own newspapers and TV stations.

Damien: Why that?

Jordon: So when there's dirty linen in a biz we own it doesn't become known.

Damien: How 'bout news sources you don't own?

Jordon: The business buys advertising spaces from those places. Have you noticed that scandalous stories about grocery stores never appear in newspapers? That's because grocery stores pay for lots of newspaper ads.

Damien: That protection racket's not what a small store can afford to play.

Jordon: My dear boy, there's no money to be made by aiming low. It's big businesses that earn the dough. The really big ones are chains that use mass media to broadcast their ads across a big city, or even a state.

Damien: I know someone who wants to start a restaurant. Can't he buy ads for just a neighborhood?

Jordon: Only costly printed ads cover small neighborhoods. Well, 'til recently, when NextDoor and News Here Now came along.

Damien: Are there other tricks?

Jordon: Doing tricks keeps a corporation as busy as an escort in Las Vegas during convention season. Another trick is big corporations hire the big four accounting firms to get around laws that were co-written by those big four accounting firms.

Damien: Tha's, er, a sweet deal for corporations. Are there yet other tricks?

Jordon: As many as an eagle has feathers. The most important trick is to give political campaign contributions to political candidates who, after the election, pass laws that give our businesses tax break after tax break. That's why big businesses pay six-figure salaries so freely.

Damien: Ah yes, money in politics. I know 'bout that. Bu' I don't yet understand how it works. Non-rich voters greatly outnumber th' wealthy, so how can dinero outweigh those votes?

Jordon: We've infiltrated both parties. This is how we control who wins the primary elections of both parties. So general elections are between a puppet Republican and a puppet Democrat.

Damien: Yeah, puppets win. I knew tha' part. But I hadn't noticed th' infiltration tactic.

Jordon: Republican voters assume Democrats are dimwits, and Democratic voters assume Republicans are dimwits. In the primary, the winner's always from the correct party, so the money bias goes unchallenged. In the general election it's too late. For added insurance in a tight race we might give a bit of money to the one we hate. But we give far more to the one we favor. That way we can't lose.

Damien: Why don't news reporters expose how 't works?

Jordon: That flow of money is harder to follow than a mouse running through a cornfield. Such as when rich wives register as Democrats and give family money to conservative Democratic politicians during primary elections.

Damien: There's somethin' else going on isn't there?

Jordon: You are bright! Yes, we pay news sources to entertain and distract. The biggest of distractions are those endless debates about issues of religion.

Damien: Religion?

Jordon: Abortion is the really useful one. The Republican party squeezes that for all it's worth.

Damien: So th' Republican party doesn't really care 'bout abortion?

Jordon: We sorta care, but not as much as tax breaks and subsidies and our legal monopolies.

Damien: I 'ave to admit voters don't see through that. They're so distracted by th' fight between left 'n right.

Jordon: They are suckers. They believe the enemy of their enemy is their friend.

Damien: Even I know that's stupid. So, how do ya know which candidates to fund, 'n by how much?

Jordon: The consultants we hire tell us where the money should go.

Damien: 'N how do those consultants know which puppets, er, politicians to bribe, er, fund?

Jordon: They monopolize their secrets, their strategies. They're like astrologers and alchemists from long ago. Back before science tanked the profits from selling horoscopes, farmer's almanacs, and Doctor Dan's mighty healing elixer.

Jordon: Politicians know, right?

Jordon: I've never asked. It just works. If it aint broke, there's no need to fix its quirks, right?

Damien: I'm not dubious, but I'm curious. How's it work?

Jordon: Curiosity killed the cat.

Damien: Satisfaction brought him back. So perhaps is there a politician ya know who might be willin' to explain how it works — so I can earn more money your way? For my fiancé.

Jordon: I do know the recipient of lots of my dough. He recently retired from Congress. Maybe he knows how it works.

Damien: Is there somethin' I can do for you, if you can maybe arrange that?

Jordon: Indeed, you can. Come up with a better business plan. A unicorn I can brag about.

Damien: I'll try. 'N now I know what barriers t' jump over to get to my big dreams of financial success. You've taught me much. I confess I'm grateful t' learn your process.

Jordon: I'm happy to give advice to young hard-working men who adore dinero. Especially if you can help me earn more.

Damien: I'll do my best t' rise to th' very top. [Whispers.] 'N get to th' bottom of th' corruption. [Normal voice.] Thank you so much for taking time t' share your wisdom.

Jordon: You're welcome! And remember the trick.

Damien: Startin' with respect, then steppin' on toes, anything goes.

Scene 3, Behind The Political Curtain

D (Damien): [Speaks to himself.] Hmm. That's an odd campaign slogan. ... Let's put corruption behind us. ... Ah, maybe this is him.

F (Finckster): Thank you for waiting.

D: Thank you for your time Congressman Finckster.

F: Come into my office ... and pardon the mess. I keep hearing promises ... that someone will clean this all up. Alas, it was hit by a fresh tomato. I mean tornado.

D: I knew politics was messy.

F: While I'm looking for bugs, would you like some cold pizza? The sausage is pork.

D: Not if that's where the bugs have been holdin' their rallies. 'N the cheeze looks more counterfeit than a spray-on tan.

F: Oh man, not those kinds of bugs. We politicians need to keep our secrets unknown ... from political spies. In fact, turn off your phone, and I'll tell you no lies.

D: Deal! Powering down, no live feed, no recording.

F: Jordon told me to trust you with behind-the-curtain and under-the-trap-door kinds of magic that we use on the political stage.

D: What a treat! A wise sage!

F: Of course you already realize we have to tell lies to voters. If we told the voters what we tell our donors, we'd never win our prize, re-election.

D: I suppose your donors keep better track of your promises.

F: They certainly make more of a fuss 'cause they hire lobbyists to keep track of us. They make sure the wording of each law complies with their bosses' desires. Yet the biggest political trick isn't deceipt. It's distraction.

D: You've got my full attention.

F: As you know there are names for the left and the right. Names like liberals, conservatives, capitalists, workers, and environmentalists. And there's name-calling. Names like tree huggers, socialists, racists, and dimwits. Those left-and-right names entertainingly distract from the fact that there's a bigger conflict.

D: What's bigger than the fight between left 'n right?

F: Allow me to introduce you to a new way to view the political terrain.

D: My brain is open wide 'n ready to be stupified.

F: The much bigger fight is between the political up and the political down.

D: Political up? Political down? Where did left and right go to? What's up?

F: The political up, that's where most voters are.

D: Voters of which party?

F: Both parties.

D: How can that be? Both Republicans and Democrats are in the political up?

F: Stop thinking of voters as Republicans and Democrats. It's us politicians, and the party insiders, who are Republicans and Democrats.

D: So is this like Star Wars fans also can be Star Trek fans? And the opposite?

F: Heck, if this is news to you, maybe you too have failed to recognize that both parties are controlled by people who utilize money.

D: That part I knew.

F: The biggest campaign contributors are in the political down.

D: The biggest contributors? Should we be puttin' down fat people?

F: Not that kind of biggest. They give the biggest amounts of money. They provide the money source that lifts us politicians high in the polls. They've bought our souls. Without their dough we get dashed against the rocks during a primary.

D: You're talkin' 'bout rich folks, right?

F: Of course they're all rich. But some of the rich are in the political up.

D: How can that be? I'm as confused as if I just stepped out from an industrial laundry washer during the high-spin cycle.

F: Confused by the spin. That's the state most voters are in. That's the aim of the political down. So of course they resist adopting a name.

D: But among themselves they call themselves the political down?

F: No, that's just how I think of them.

D: This upfront lowdown is blindingly illuminatin'.

F: Of course the political down prefers our party, the Republican party.

D: That I can see.

F: But also the political down has infiltrated the Democratic party.

D: Whoa! How come the political down donates money to both parties? That's as stupid as placin' first-place bets on both horses in a two-horse race.

F: Ah, here's a big secret. They mostly only assist Democratic candidates during primary elections. Of course I'm simplifying hugely.

D: Ah, I see! They use money to influence who wins each Democratic primary race. But in the general election they just embrace Republican candidates?

F: Isn't it brilliant? Yet subtle. Like a gleeming-smile model in an auto ad.

D: Now I'm beginnin' to see how come we, er, most voters, dislike both candidates, the Republican and the Democrat. I don't mean any disrespect.

F: We politicians expect a lack of respect. We know we're stuck in the middle. Between voters and our biggest campaign contributors. Now do you see why voters are distracted by the entertaining conflict between left and right?

D: Instead of words I need a picture.

F: It's sort of like when ancient Roman rulers distracted plebians with bloody fighting among slaves in their immense Colosseum. Except that modern-day plebians get to vote which slave, er, puppet, wins the staged fight.

D: So it's like pickin' pockets while celebrities are on stage?

F: That's a bit rough. But close enough.

D: With their clout, what's the political down really care about?

F: Profits for the businesses they own. What especially delights them are biz tax breaks. And when they can get a legal monopoly they cling to it like a Titanic passenger would clutch a chunk of styrofoam.

D: Wow! Those business owners pay politicians for lower taxes 'n no competition. That deal's sweet! But that's cheatin'. It's corrupt. Am I wrong?

F: You're right.

D: I'm confused. On the political right, the Republican party seems to care about some non-business issues like abortions, and gay marriage, Christian values, immigration, 'n such, right?

F: They do glorify those things on the flag they fly. But taxes, and ideally subsidies and monopolies, are their real priorities. That's because party insiders, in both parties, get their marching orders from the biggest campaign contributors.

D: Now I think I'm seein' how come neither political party really gives a damn 'bout protectin' coral reefs, fixin' climate change, givin' homeless folks an assist, or listenin' to what dolphins have to say about us dumpin' trash into their swimmin' pool. I see the down folks are usin' religious 'n racial issues to divide 'n distract.

F: Here's another division tactic. Money can fund extreme liberal agendas. Like when the LGB category got extended. To include queers and transgenders. That scares voters to the right.

D: Yeah, out of spite many voters blindly believe the enemy of their enemy is their friend.

F: That's a powerful political tactic.

D: About those monopolies. 'Course I know I don't dare start a business that competes with a millionare's. What else should I get my head around?

F: Indeed, you can't start an insurance company, and you can't design a bridge without an engineering degree.

D: Those make sense.

F: You could brew a beer, but to sell your beer in stores you'd have to cut a deal with one of the two big beer distributors who monopolize store shelf space.

D: Fortunately brewin' beer's not my thing.

F: You also can't earn much money selling the herb stevia as a sweetener for drinks because laws block stevia from appearing on grocery shelves next to sugar or next to artificial sweeteners.

D: So stevia's a natural sweetener? But it can't be found where it would cut into profits for sugar companies? 'N makers of artificial sweeteners?

F: Yup. And speaking of sugar, long ago Congress passed a law against buying sugar that's grown outside the U.S.

D: That sounds like an inside scam.

F: Here in the states we pay way more, sometimes almost twice the price, compared to other nations.

D: Coffee'd taste sweeter without that price hike.

F: And it's easy to hide the giving of funds to both sides. In fact there are two brothers in Florida in the sugar biz. One brother is a Republican who gives buckets of money to Republican politicians. The other brother is a Democrat who gives buckets of money to Democratic politicians. Ain't that sweet?

D: 'N as hard to follow as a rat chased by a cat. So they don't give a damn 'bout left or right? They just lobby for sugar ...

F: Subsidies. Especially the canals that sustain Florida farmers who grow sugarcane. But the biggest financial gain comes from converting sugarcane into sugar, and that's what's done by the businesses those bros own.

D: That's a sour deal for us. How come this isn't more obvious?

F: On commodity price lists, they used to list sugar and U.S. sugar by those names. But now the names are sugar number eleven and sugar number sixteen.

D: That's a slick trick. Um, there's somethin' else that's a bit fuzzy. Don't some rich folks prefer the Democratic party?

F: Lots of lawyers get lots of their business from Democratic voters, so they like Democratic politicians. And then there are industries that subdivide into left and right.

D: Huh? I thought I was followin' you down main street, but you just ducked into a dark alley.

F: Banks prefer the Republican party. 'N credit unions prefer the Democratic party.

D: Wow! I think now I'm seein' who's in the political down. 'N how come they oppose us, the voters, their suckers, in the political up. But how do so very few rich folks outvote us, the non-rich, who outnumber them? Like hairs outnumber whiskers on a walrus.

F: There's something in politics called vote splitting.

D: What do spittin' goats have to do with politics?

F: Not goats. Votes. As in voting.

D: Vote spittin'?

F: Not spitting, although long ago there was lots of spitting in politics. It's splitting, vote splitting, and it's the election version of divide and conquer.

D: Ah, vote splitting.

F: That's it!

D: 'N divide 'n conquer. Isn't that the battle tactic armies use when they separate enemy soldiers from one another? 'N then they can attack the smaller groups when they're aloner?

F: Yes, and in fact, voting is rooted in war and fighting. That's why women didn't vote. They weren't counted because they didn't fight. Of course, those counting experts never met my brother's ex-wife.

D: [Chuckles.]

F: That counting was done to figure out how many men would be in each gang. And then the smallest gangs negotiate and join forces. Otherwise they get slaughtered.

D: So the winner's the side that joins the most gangs into just one very big army?

F: Yes, and the remaining gangs join together to form the opposition army. So it comes down to two armies. And that's where size matters.

D: Ah, so long ago votin' began as a way to count potential army sizes. 'N the smaller army surrenders?

F: Saves a lot of dying, no? And when splitting can't be done physically, then splitting psychologically works too. In politics, that's what religious differences do.

D: So how does this vote splitting work?

F: Well, it involves math.

D: Oh dear, ya mean, mathematics?

F: Certainly.

D: In my opinion math's the devil's favorite form of torture. If I had to choose between doin' just one page of math homework, or standin' under a tall fir tree gettin' cut down, I'd be there yellin' timber!

F: I don't like it either. And I don't understand vote splitting well enough to clearly explain how it all works. I just know that it works. So we, the politicians, are effectively hobbled and handcuffed and gagged when we cast our votes in Congress.

D: Ya said there's distractions. How can just distractions hide this vote splittin' so effectively?

F: You've heard of the electoral college? And gerrymandering?

D: I admit long ago I wondered if Jerry Mander was someone important. Now I realize those're 'bout the attention-grabbin' fight between Republicans and Democrats.

F: That's why news reporters are not blocked from writing and speaking about those unfairness topics.

D: Which now I know helps distract from, 'n hide, the bigger fight between political up 'n political down.

F: And you've heard of the money bonus that a third-party presidential candidate can get if they get more than a certain percent of the vote?

D: Aha! That's a tactic to split votes away from ... well who?

F: Third parties are almost always on the left. At least in the U.S. Whenever needed they're quietly seeded with funds from conservatives. That splits votes away from the Democratic nominee.

D: I see. It just affects the distractin' balance between left 'n right.

F: And if a conservative third-party candidate begins to do well in the polls, they get a bribe to drop out. That concentrates conservative voters' ballots on the single Republican nominee.

D: 'N now I see how come news media 'n those slippery political ads don't have as much influence as many folks suppose. The splittin' of votes among candidates durin' primaries, that's their key to controllin' you politicians. Like puppets, er, well, like I'm not sure what.

F: That's not what I like to hear. Yet between you and me, the political down is my puppet master, the puppeteer.

D: 'N yet we have social media. Aren't there some bright wits callin' attention to these dirty politics?

F: To deal with that the political down hires critics to write comments in forums, to record podcasts, and to tweet photoshopped evidence that proves whatever, like how JFK shot first. Plus they hire coders to make bots that upvote their propaganda, and downvote the honest truth. Plus they track and target gullible voters. Especially the ones who believe that eggs, colorful ones no less, come from rabbits.

D: On Easter. I've never understood that either. Now I know how come some people online attack with such anger. Lots of 'em are gettin' paid to be a faker?

F: Yup. Mister Mischievious from Michigan is getting paid to inspire Furious Fiona from Florida to re-post the clever meme he created to trash Hillary Clinton. And you should know attack ads also work. Because lots of voters get swayed by believing that expression the enemy of my enemy is my friend.

D: That's stupid. Don't they see that just means they're shootin' at the same target?

F: And getting hit by friendly fire! Yes that particular stupidity is especially easy to exploit. And it's more common than ants in line for dropped fast food.

D: I think I'm figurin' this out. It's not what I expected. Yet it makes too much sense to be fictional.

F: There's one bit of history I should teach you.

D: Oh I hate history. Crammin' more facts 'bout the Alamo 'n the Civil War into my head might crowd out what I've stuffed in here.

F: This is simple. Back when primary elections were uncommon, vote splitting was obvious. There was just one election, the one we now call the general election. Sometimes a political party offered two or even three candidates. If the other big party offered just one candidate, that solo one won.

D: Ah, 'cause voters in the losin' party would split their votes among their similar candidates. The divide and conquer tactic.

F: The winning strategy came to be for each party to have their own primary. The idea was to discover which politician deserves the solo spot. In what we now call the general election.

D: Ah! Now the splittin's hidden in primaries. Where the winner's never from the wrong party.

F: Indeed! You learn fast! So here's a test.

D: Oh dear lord! I hate tests! 'N this might be 'bout history no less.

F: Let go of that foolish fear. This answer should be clear.

D: [Sighs.] 'Kay

F: What helped Barack Obama win the two thousand eight Democratic primary election against Hillary Clinton?

D: Based on what you've taught, some wealthy business owners may have thought, ... that well, ...

F: You're on the right track.

D: ... thought to give money to Obama to defeat their bigger enemy, Clinton.

F: Correct so far.

D: 'N they probably made the assumption that a black man couldn't win the general election. Is that right?

F: You did it! That's right! Although of course we cannot trace all donations. But that's a pattern that often happens.

D: The Republicans ... er, fans of Republican politicians, who gave contributions to Obama must've chuckled when they donated. Then raged for days when they got an African American president.

F: And that gives you an example of a blocking tactic that wouldn't work if vote splitting were not such a useful gimmick for rigging elections.

D: I heard what you said. But the words leaked out of my brain without leaving behind any idea 'bout what they mean.

F: If unfair vote splitting were to disappear, then that blocking kind of tactic wouldn't interfere. That's because in the general election, each party would offer two or three selections, candidates.

D: Ah, it's becomin' clear. So what can make the evil split disappear?

F: I really don't know, and don't care. The political stress was making a mess of my ulcers. Giving them their own ulcers. So I retired. That's why I can risk speaking candidly. But remember you didn't learn any of this from me. If you go to newspaper reporters with these insights I'll shine light on the skeletons in the closet of your friend Jordon. He asked me to help you on your mission to earn money using his tricks.

D: I won't be a snitch or fink. 'N anyways I can't yet link the problem of vote splittin' to a solution. One that can defeat this unfairness. So I need to learn more. Do you know who would know how to fix this mess? The unfair politics?

F: Probably that would be a professor of mathematics.

D: Aye, mental gymnastics! In math no less. That's too advanced. I'd pee in my pants, it scares me so!

F: Well I've got to go. I wish you luck in understanding yet more so maybe someday you can help clean up the muck on the political stage. In the meantime, the political world is upside down. Voters mistakenly assume the rich are at the top. Yes, politicians have all been bought. But as voters you've got more power than the SpaceX rockets, a swarm of locusts, and a flu virus, all working together on the same team.

D: So you think maybe someday the voters will, uh, ...

F: ... reign supreme? Eventually. Hopefully. Then us politicians will become your puppets. But currently we're the puppets of wealthy business owners.

D: I admit I'm seein' a bit of hope for a fix. To get less dysfunctional politics. Now I know the greedy rich distract us with left versus right. Yet up versus down, that's the real fight.

F: You're bright. Good luck! But don't forget, it was some other schmuck who gave you the tour of the elephant and donkey muck.

D: Thank you for tiltin' my brain to better see the political terrain. You've saved me from going insane.

Scene 4, Fighting Against Darkness

Desha: [Sitting on a stone bench in a cemetery eating a cookie.] You're way late. And don't call this a date.

Damien: 'R you Desha?

Desha: Who else would be in this spot in this cemetery at this time?

Damien: Nice t' meet ya. I'm Damien.

Desha: Of course.

Damien: Thanks f'r meetin' wi' me.

Desha: For nothing.

Damien: Huh?

Desha: That's the meaning of de nada in Spanish.

Damien: Yeah I know. M' mom's Puerto Rican.

Desha: Then why did you ask?

Damien: Is there cannibis in tha' cookie?

Desha: No you can't have one.

Damien: I jus' wondered what's in it.

Desha: Chocolate chips, dried cherries, oatmeal, stevia, sugar, and ghee, but nothing funny.

Damien: Ya said you wanted to meet wi' me.

Desha: Congressman Finckster said I should meet with you.

Damien: T' discuss why politics is so dysfunctional, y' said.

Desha: Damn right! It's so so so dysfunctional.

Damien: So, did he tell ya about vote splittin'?

Desha: What do goats have to do with politics?

Damien: Not goats. Not spitting. Vote splitting.

Desha: Splitting votes in half? That's a half-wit idea.

Damien: Not splitting ballots. Splitting voters.

Desha: That's murder. Yes politicians do murder innocent people by their flawed laws.

Damien: That's not what vote splitting is.

Desha: Then it sounds quite esoteric. What's important is that too many people are suffering under cruel corruption.

Damien: Yeah, corruption's so unfair. It's like leavin' just four squares o' toilet paper on'a toilet paper roll.

Desha: It's millions of times worse. Corruption kills through economic suffering that leads to suicide, homicide, overdoses, homelessness, and more. Corruption kills by allowing gun makers to push assault rifles into the hands of mentally unbalanced young males. And corruption kills pedestrians by giving preference to cars. And the companion of corruption is despair. Life is so unfair.

Damien: Th' companion of corruption is despair, if that's from th' Bible I've never heard it, bu' I agree.

Desha: Get to the point.

Damien: Vote splittin's at the root of unfair elections, so do ya wanna hear about it?

Desha: Tell me how you think it makes a difference.

Damien: Here's uh way to understand it. Suppose there's four politicians.

Desha: What are their names?

Damien: I dunno. This is just a generic example.

Desha: Generic is dead, like the people here. Let's bring it to life. You describe them, I'll name them.

Damien: Two of 'em are puppets of wealthy business owners. Th' other two promise to reduce corruption, so they're more popular.

Desha: The names of the first two are Pinoke and Oscar.

Damien: Huh?

Desha: Pinoke is a nickname for Pinnochio, the puppet. And Oscar's last name is the Grouch. He lives in trash just like corrupt politicians.

Damien: OK. Whatever.

Desha: The other two are named Barack, 'cause we can hope for change, and Hypatia 'cause women should rule.

Damien: Wi' these four live candidates, who'd win?

Desha: Either Barack or Hypatia, obviously, 'cause voters want less corruption. They don't want puppets, not Pinoke, not Oscar.

Damien: Right. 'N the voters would get what they want. Bu' then big-money donors arrive.

Desha: So, now you'll say that their money buys advertising that hypnotizes the voters. The way headlights freeze baby rabbits?

Damien: Only th' terminally stupid'd fall for that.

Desha: So tell me why you think money changes who wins.

Damien: Wealthy business owners, who're th' biggest campaign donors, in private they choose which puppet gets their money. If they like th' look of Pinoke's nose, then Oscar's paid t' hike th' Appalachian trail.

Desha: That would make Oscar a grouch. What if he should refuse?

Damien: They point out he'll lose. Without their dollars. 'R they bribe 'im with favors, if that's what it takes.

Desha: A dumpster full of cookies?

Damien: Or a subscription t' Grouch Magazine if that floats his boat. That'd leave Pinoke and Hypatia and Barack. Who'd win that three-way race?

Desha: Ah, lots of voters would split their votes between Barack and Hypatia. That would make it easier for Pinoke to win.

Damien: Plus Cock Brothers 'n Forbes levels of dollars'd pay for ads that attack Hypatia and Barack. Plus news coverage that favors Pinoke. That'd be enough t' rig th' race.

Desha: A puppet wins. That's unfair! More voters prefer either Barack or Hypatia.

Damien: That's what I've learned. Bu' now I'm stuck. I dunno how t' change elections so they don't suck.

Desha: We can call attention to this deception. We'll get voters to concentrate their votes on either Barack or Hypatia.

Damien: Bu' who decides which candidate to dump?

Desha: We the voters could get one to vacate their spot, right?

Damien: Tha' would coax th' wealthiest campaign donors t' quietly fund yet another candidate. One who also promises t' reduce corruption.

Desha: Let's name this one Ghandi. Yes, that tactic's difficult to beat. It splits the voters even more, making it even harder to defeat their single puppet.

Damien: All that happens in primary elections. Then in th' general elections we have to choose between th' two puppets, one from each party.

Desha: Now it makes even more sense why we have just two main political parties.

Damien: Yup. 'N years ago th' puppet politicians passed a law t' give funding t' a third-party presidential candidate who gets more than five percent of th' vote.

Desha: I thought that was a good thing. Now I see it's a bribe that seduces liberals into splitting their votes. While conservatives quietly concentrate their votes on just one candidate.

Damien: You learn fast.

Desha: I have a degree in political science. But they never taught us this.

Damien: Th' unfairness is hidden. It's hidden by numbers, 'n math to me is scary.

Desha: What scares me is that our planet is losing snow leopards and elephants, and rhinoceros ... es, and dolphins, and corral reefs, and plant species that could cure and feed.

Damien: Is tha' what got you into politics?

Desha: At the age of fourteen, ... my mother died. And that's when lots of people, especially my father, lied. They told me everything would turn out fine.

Damien: I can't imagine what 't would be like to lose someone so close. At such a young age.

Desha: I can't either. It's still unreal. Especially because just six years later my brother was killed in the Middle East.

Damien: How did'ya cope?

Desha: I almost lost hope. Then I realized my mother was killed by incompetent city officials. They failed to time pedestrian walk signals to give walkers a head start. Before the green light for cars. And I realized, that basically, my brother was defending profits for oil companies in the Middle East.

Damien: Is tha' why we're in this graveyard?

Desha: My mother and brother are buried over there.

Damien: Ah.

Desha: Over time I traced the local corruption to the state level, then to DC, then to Congress where they write laws so corrupt.

Damien: Yeah, corruption. I wouldn't know how t' define it, bu' I sure see lots of it.

Desha: It's betrayal, bribery, cheating, and coersion, cronyism, deceitfulness, deluding, and deviousness, dishonesty, duplicity, and embezzelment, entrapment, fraud, and graft, misleading, misrepresenting, and monopolizing, palm greasing, payoffs, swindling, and tax evasion, treachery, underhandedness, unethicalness, unscrupulousness, and wickedness. Not to mention lying and littering.

Damien: Littering?

Desha: It's a gateway crime.

Damien: Huh?

Desha: Like not picking up dog poop, 'n not wearing a face mask during an epidemic.

Damien: Your brain is on another wild ride?

Damien: A dog owner doesn't pick up her dog's poop because her dog will poke it with his snout. She picks it up so other dogs don't poke it with their snouts. In return, those other dog owners protect her dog by picking up their dog's poop. It's a poop scooper loop. And the same kind of loop works with face masks during an epidemic.

Damien: 'Kay ....

Desha: In other words, corruption's a situation where someone can get something by not caring about the suffering of others.

Damien: Tha' makes sense.

Desha: I have a tatoo that helps remind me to keep fighting that fight.

Damien: Against people who don't, er, participate in ... super pupper ... pooper scooper loops? C'n I see it? Th' tatoo?

Desha: Fighting against corruption. It's for private tours only.

Damien: What's it say?

Desha: After I realized the real causes of the deaths of my mother and brother, I decided to kick some ... sense into the political world. The tatoo's a reminder to kick ass, and not stop fighting.

Damien: Who're you fighting?

Desha: I've hit another turning point. Originally I thought the enemy was capitalism, and that socialism was the opposite.

Damien: An' it's not?

Desha: It's not that simple. Then I fought against the Republican party. But recently I realized the Democratic party has been infiltrated by big-money donors.

Damien: I too jus' learned th' Republican party isn't th' real enemy.

Desha: My anger is rising. So I need to figure out, and soon, whose butt I should kick.

Damien: I think I've found th' tipping point.

Desha: The place where a little effort can make a huge change?

Damien: Yeah, bu' that path's blocked.

Desha: By what?

Damien: Math. It's blockin' me from figuring out how t' turn th' world right side up.

Desha: I got as far as algebra and trig and statistics without tearing out my hair. What d'you wanna figure out?

Damien: How should votes be counted to get results that're fair?

Desha: I don't know. Bu' I do know someone who might know th' answer.

Damien: C'n he teach us ...

Desha: Wrong gender.

Damien: Who's she?

Desha: She's a math prof.

Damien: Uh professor of math?

Desha: Yes, at the state university. That's where I got my degree.

Damien: I couldn't cope with even commun'ty college. 'N textbooks hold weasely words that try t' drag my brain to useless destinations.

Desha: So you're a loser.

Damien: Huh?

Desha: You're choosing to give up instead of fight. That's losing.

Damien: I'm not brainy. How do I fight against math?

Desha: What took you this far?

Damien: I'm short 'n not handsome. So workin' hard t' earn money is all I've got t' keep my fiancé happy.

Desha: What's so special about her?

Damien: Sh' appreciates me, even though I'm notta hunk surround'd by adoring women.

Desha: All you need is one.

Damien: D' you have someone?

Desha: I have my Willie.

Damien: Whoa! Say what?

Desha: My partner's name is Willie.

Damien: Are you two happy? You and your ... Willie?

Desha: What's your disability? Did you never learn to read? Do the words migrate across the page like a musk ox? Do you nod off on page three and spill your hot cocoa on your ... lap? There's gotta be somethin' more.

Damien: It hurts t' read. Th' words're a pain t' look at.

Desha: Have you tried color-tinted glasses?

Damien: Huh? I don't follow.

Desha: Of course not. Never mind. I'll send you to a website where you can find out more. In the meantime, do you want me to arrange a meeting with this math prof?

Damien: 'K bu' only if she can explain things in spoken words 'n not use lots of jargon, or academic speak.

Desha: I think she can be OK with that. 'N maybe I can translate if that's what you really need.

Damien: It's what I need. What d'you need?

Desha: In my early youth we were so happy then, even though money we lacked. Then the world turned upside down. I saw suffering that I hadn't seen before. And I traced the cause of suffering to corruption in government. Those ... grrr ... politicians are the puppets of greedy money huggers. Now I want to send them to hell, those greedy evil buggers.

Damien: Which ones? Th' politicians or th' big campaign contributors?

Desha: Whoever is most to blame.

Damien: From what I can tell, they're both clueless. About why money works so well as puppet strings. Can we fight against cluelessness?

Desha: If it would help to carry a banner that says End Cluelessness Now I will. I'll fight against whoever's to blame.

Damien: So what's your plan?

Desha: I call on the spirits of the dead here to inspire me to find a way to shine a light on corruption. I want a light that is so bright that even evil money huggers and egotistic puppets cannot fight back. Not with their wealth, not with lawyers, and not through hired workers. I know that light casts out darkness. In that light the path to better times will appear. Until that happens I'll keep on fighting. Fighting with words. Fighting with deeds. Doing whatever it takes to bring good times back to us, the voters, the majority.

Damien: Whatever it takes? Yeah, 't seems it'll take some looking into mathematics.

Desha: I'm willing to help you fight against your fear of math. Let's do this!

Damien: I'm ready to fight! I jus' hope there's no evil fractions. Otherwise I'm ready t' find out how to turn th' world right side up. [better final line?]

Scene 5, Math Breakthrough

De (Desha): Hi professor Mata. This is Damien.

M (Mata): Welcome Desha and Damien. Let's go into the classroom to talk. By the way, Damien, do you like pi?

D (Damien): In the morning pie seems so irrational.

M: So you do like math?

D: Already I'm confused.

De: He doesn't know about those special meanings in the math world. Just assume he knows as much about math as Mozart knew about ... electronics. Plus he has tons of fear around fractions. That's Damien. I don't know if Mozart had that fear.

D: Classrooms are scary, spooky, 'n terrifyin'. This one's bringin' back awful memories of bein' teased for gettin' Cs, 'n Ds, 'specially in math 'n history.

M: I bet you're smart. You just didn't get a good start. Can you count?

D: One two three four 'n of course there's more.

M: Can you go the other way?

D: Four three two one.

M: What comes after one?

D: Nothin'.

M: In a way you're right.

D: Thanks for bein' polite in sayin' I'm wrong.

M: What's nothing called in math?

D: Oh, zero.

M: Ah yes, wonderful magical zero!

D: What's so special 'bout zero?

M: Zero as a digit was not known in ancient Egypt, Babylon, Greece, and Rome. But in ancient China they put their counting marks inside a square. So when no marks are there, it's an empty square. That changed to a circle as the idea spread to India then Arabic-speaking universities. And then a student took it to Rome and became pope. He could calculate faster than the Italians who still used counting marks, the ones we call Roman numerals. That's how the digit zero became part of the Italian Renaissance.

De: That's when Leonardo painted the Mona Lisa, and Michelangelo carved the rock-hard anatomy of David.

D: Lisa and David. I think I've heard about those two.

M: With that digit zero, sailors made realistic maps, and navigated far out into the Atlantic. That avoided the north-bound winds that block the path along the south coast of Africa. That path, which bumped into Brazil, took them around the southern tip of Africa. With that sea route Europeans bypassed the monopoly that Arabic-speaking Muslims had on the land-based silk road to China.

De: So it was the digit zero, not Columbus, that got us to North and South America?

M: Yes, in fact, the Portuguese discovered Brazil before fourteen ninety two.

D: Ah, so that's why people in Brazil speak Portuguese instead of Spanish.

De: Interesting!

D: OK, zero's a big-deal number.

M: The digit zero. Not just zero. There have always been words like none, empty, nobody, ziltch, naked, hungry, and moron. But writing four zero zero instead of C C C C, that's magic.

D: So the digit zero's a big deal.

De: Without it bridges would be filled with long lines of accountants waiting for their turn to jump off.

M: Without it, scientists and engineers couldn't have put a man on the moon, or put rovers on the planet Mars, or photographed the rings of Saturn from within those rings. And those are just a few of the things that make the digit zero so incredibly fantastic.

D: I think my confusions 'bout zero are gone. But how's that relate to what happens in gettin' fair elections?

M: There's something still very new, not yet taught in public schools, that can take civilization, humanity, us, to the next level where elections are fair. But to get there you need to appreciate the power of a name.

D: OK, what's the name?

M: A name without it's meaning is useless. Concepts come first.

D: Every test I took cared more about the names than the concepts.

De: I learned to spell hypotenuse before I learned it had nothing to do with hippos.

M: That's because names and dates and such are easier to test.

D: Isn't that upside down? Testin' what's less important?

M: You seem to me to be quite intelligent. So let's eliminate your fear of fractions.

D: Is there a rattlesnake cage or fallin' tree nearby?

M: Ancient Babylonians also disliked fractions. And so did the Romans. It's because they lacked the digit zero. That's no big deal for addition and subtraction and multiplication. Those are just shortcuts for counting up, counting down, and a skipping version of counting up. But division, without the big-deal zero, that's muddled and befuddled confusion. So leaving numbers as fractions, without doing the division it signifies, that's what they did until the digit zero materialized.

D: Now we've got zero, the digit. Yet I've gotta use fractions every day. It makes me wacko to add 'n subtract those suckers.

M: If fractions you loathe, then this question I pose. Why do you use them?

D: It's part of my job.

M: Are you a musician?

De: What's music got to do with fractions?

M: Musicians cannot avoid fractions. They count by two, or three, or four, or six, or eight. But not by five or ten. Except, I suspect, for some geeky modern jazz.

De: Now we know that Mozart didn't fear fractions.

D: I build custom staircases. Tape measures are marked in halves, quarters, eighths, 'n sixteenths. Those effin' fractions. I'd murder those suckers if I knew where to aim.

M: Use decimal numbers. That's what the whole world uses, as part of the metric system. Except of course here in the states.

D: I can't use metric units. That'd get me fired. Inches and feet are required.

M: Decimal numbers work with inches too. Just get a tape measure with decimal markings for inches!

D: Oh, if only I could do so. That'd be great! I could avoid the fractions I hate!

M: Here, look at this tape measure.

D: Ah, it's marked with ten units per inch! When I measure I could write the numbers as tenths or hundredths. 'N it shows eighths as well. This is, well, swell!

M: And adding and subtracting them is as easy as dollars and cents.

De: So a fraction is a division problem unfinished. It's waiting to get diminished to a single number.

D: Using this tape measure would be a pleasure. How do I get one?

M: Use the magic math word decimal when you search for tape measure.

D: Ah, words can be powerful.

M: You learn fast! Now about your fear of fractions. Ancient Romans, even though they fearlessly conquered most Mediterranean waterfront property, they too had that fear. They liked the number twelve. That's why sundials have twelve marks for the day.

De: So that's why we have twenty four hours per day?

M: Indeed. The number twelve can be divided by two and three and four and six, and yield a nice result of six or four or three or two.

D: I wondered why time is measured in numbers that aren't in multiples of ten.

M: Sexagesimal.

D: We're jumpin' from fractions to sex?

De: Using fractions as foreplay would solve the world's overpopulation problem.

M: Sexagesimal is the name for using sixty as a base. That's what the ancient Babylonians chose. Sixty divides without remainders by two and three and four and five and six and ten and twelve and fifteen and twenty and thirty. That's why an hour has sixty minutes. And why a minute has sixty seconds.

D: So we could ditch fractions? That's a world I'd like to see.

M: So are fractions a bit less scary?

D: Yes, I'm not in fear of them as much. But sometimes I get stuck not knowing when to do division, in the right sequence with addition 'n subtraction.

M: That's just the trick of algebra.

D: Oh dear lord please forget I said that! From what I've heard, algebra's the fifth horseman of the apocalypse.

M: Albert Einstein, when he was young, also had trouble with algebra.

De: But he was a genius. And best known for E equals M C squared, the ultimate celebrity math equation.

M: He struggled until his uncle told him to think of algebra as a whodunnit mystery. Where the identity of mister X is unknown, and the facts are clues, and the goal is to figure out who is mister X?

De: Why didn't my algebra teacher teach that trick?

M: Because donning a Sherlock Holmes cap in class would get you sent to the principal's office. And writing whodunnit on a standardized test would get you sent to the circus as a clown.

D: Ah, I think I'm seein' your point. Division asks the question: What number needs to be multiplied times the number on the bottom of a fraction to get the number on the top of the fraction? Right?

M: Excellent! Now you understand some key ideas of math. Not enough for me to be inclined to drive over a bridge you designed. There's lots more. And yet, so much of it would make sense if math history were taught with a focus on concepts. It even explains why we say fourteen and thirteen but not two-teen and one-teen.

De: I suppose this explains why hotel elevators can't count to thirteen.

D: I sure feel unlucky when I'm stuck with a measurement of thirteen instead of twelve 'n have to divide it.

M: Here's another useful secret. Division is disguised under other names. Like ratio, rate, proportion, average, percentage, percent, and the word per. And of course fractions.

D: So a fraction's just a lazy way to deal with division?

M: You've got it.

De: It sounds like we need a revolution in how math is taught.

D: Another revolution? How many do you want?

De: As many as it takes to get things right side up.

M: Oh I do wish there was more time so we could talk about beautiful balanced equations, and what's behind calculus, and why quadratic equations ....

D: Fortunately we don't have that much time.

M: Of course, of course! And anyway, computers can do math better than students.

De: Wait a minute! Math textbooks and math professors are teaching us thinking skills that computers can easily handle? Why is that?

M: Ironic isn't it? Computers are better than humans at spelling, grammar, arithmetic, algebra, trigonometry, calculus, historical facts, geography, map reading, and diplomatically insulting you for missing a right turn. Yet we try to teach all that in school.

D: What're computers not good at doing?

M: Inventing, creating new solutions to real-life problems, writing books worth reading, composing beautiful music, scripting videos worth watching, graphic design, software development, extracting meaning from data, creative things like that.

D: Would that include designing custom staircases?

M: Definitely.

D: Those are the skills that employers desire. My boss says it's hard to hire workers who can do much more than loiter in the general vicinity of a staircase.

De: So schools teach what computers can do better? And schools fail to teach the skills that computers are not good at, but that businesses really want? Wow! The academic world is upside down!

M: Alas, the academic world is upside down for students and teachers and employers.

De: No wonder I often recall so little of what I learned in college. Computers do it better. We really ought to have a revolution in how math, and more, is taught.

M: Computers lack the ability to understand concepts. Yet too often that's what's academia fails to teach.

D: So schools deserve a failing grade! I love it!

M: Definitions, terminology, memorization of facts, grammar rules, math rules, etcetera are what professors teach because textbooks focus on them. And standardized tests test those things. But really it's the concepts that schools most need to teach.

D: Now can we switch to politics from just mathematics? I'm eager to learn the math behind voting.

M: Now you're ready. You won't be scared when zero pops up. And only one very simple fraction is involved. The one called half.

D: Hurray! Even a half wit like me can handle a half.

De: That's one divided by two. That equals zero point five.

M: Or fifty percent. Now you're ready! Let's explore how votes need to be counted for results to be fair.

D: Finally!

M: So how do you think voting should be done?

De: As you know, I'm not a math wiz. Or even a nerd.

M: Damien? What do you suppose that would look like?

D: Uh, ... I reckon, ... maybe ... it might use ... five stars? ... Like Amazon does.

M: That's a good start. And why is that approach smart?

D: If Amazon used just one star for each product, like on an 'lection ballot, that wouldn't be enough info. So what's needed in elections is more info.

M: Excellent! Yes indeed! So if stars were used in elections, and the highest count of stars indicated the winner, how could you, as a voter, get some extra influence?

D: I'm feelin' like a dunce.

M: Let's try a different scenario. Let's suppose you're in the audience at a talent contest, and the emcee announces that the loudness of clapping will determine who wins. How can you get extra influence?

D: I dunno.

De: Nor do I.

M: You could clap really loud for your favorites, and just pretend to clap for the others.

D: That'd be cheating.

M: In a talent contest, maybe, maybe not. At theater events, that's disrespectful. But in an election, with money on the line, that's just freedom of expression. It's voting, but with an unfair kind of vote counting.

De: Ah, it's fighting! Done on ballots.

D: So when I rate things on Amazon I should only use one star or five stars?

M: If you do that on Amazon you're being a jerk. But if that star rating were used in elections, where so much is at stake, that tactic would make your ballot have more impact than ballots marked honestly.

D: I'm still following things to here. Too bad I can't celebrate with a beer.

M: Bravo! You see that just collecting more information isn't enough. How the information is counted to identify a winner is so important to get right.

D: So the five star method won't work?

M: Ah, I should take a step back. There are two parts to any voting method. There's the ballot and there's the counting of those ballots.

D: What kind'a ballot do we use currently?

M: Almost every nation in the world uses what's now called the single-mark ballot.

De: 'Cause we can only mark a single choice?

M: Right. And there's just one way to count that kind of ballot. Which is why until recently that ballot didn't have a name. The counting method has different names. It's the enemy of fair voting so it's worth learning its names. In the academic world it's called plurality voting. In Canada and other British places it's called first past the post.

D: What's it called here in the states?

M: It's just called voting.

De: Ah! With no name it becomes harder to fight against! Imagine protesting with a sign that says End That Unnamed Bad Kind Of Vote Counting.

D: So that's the enemy, the single-mark ballot?

M: Yes. It is to democracy what a string and two old-style tin cans are to the telephone.

D: That's so primitive.

De: So what's the name of a ballot where each candidate can be ranked at a different level, like on Amazon?

M: That's called a ranked ballot, or a score ballot, depending on how it's counted.

D: Brain freeze big time! Is that difference really of prime importance?

M: To get the math right, yes. But both types are better than what we use now.

De: Isn't anything better than what we use now?

M: Almost anything. There's one seductive exception. That's using points, where each voter is given a limited number of points to distribute among the choices.

De: Is that because a jerk could give all his points to a single candidate?

M: That's one of its flaws. If vote counting methods competed in a limbo contest, the points approach would win the limbo contest, as the lowest. Anything else is like pole vaulting over what we use now.

D: So using ballots that are like Amazon stars .... Wait a moment. Does this mean voting has to be done electronically?

De: Paper ballots have to be allowed. Lots of people vote by mail. That's what my brother did when he was overseas. And voting machines can be hacked.

M: Paper ballots with ovals to mark work just fine. Of course columns of ovals are needed for the preference levels. Let's say there's seven columns. The columns would be labelled first choice, second choice, third choice, and so on up to seventh choice.

De: What happens if a voter marks more than one oval for the same candidate?

M: Just count the highest rank.

De: Suppose a voter doesn't mark any of a candidate's ovals.

M: That candidate is ranked at the bottom. In this case that's the seventh choice.

D: I think even I could mark that kind of ballot.

De: Anyone who can't is too stupid to be voting.

D: You're sayin' some ways of counting those ballots are better than others?

M: Exactly! If everyone is honest, then simple counting works fine.

D: Simple counting?

M: If there are five columns, a marked oval in the first choice column would be like marking five Amazon stars, a mark in the second choice column would be like marking four Amazon stars, and so on down to a mark in the fifth choice column would be like marking one Amazon star.

D: That's simple?

De: A computer would take care of doing that counting. You would just mark the correct column for each candidate.

M: Even hand counting the ballots that way would be easy. For simple counting the candidate with the highest such count would win. If everyone is honest, then that works fine.

De: Fat chance of that! Honesty I mean. It seems to be getting less and less fashionable. Especially in business and politics.

M: Yes when money is involved, as in politics, then that simple way of counting ratings is vulnerable to strategic voters. They can get extra influence using the clapping tactic.

De: I'm curious. What happens when Amazon customers realize they can get extra influence by skipping the middle ratings?

M: Then Amazon can move the goalposts. They can count differently. Actually they already do. They can get even more sophisticated if that's needed.

D: I'm confused. I understand how the ballots work. But I can't imagine a way to count votes that's not like any of what we've been discussing. I thought I was following, but now I've stumbled up another dark alley.

M: Take a deep breath! ... Or two. And give yourself an A plus! You two are learning more and faster than anyone else I've tried to explain this to.

D: Really? Or are you just tryin' to, well, I dunno. This is so different from that teacher who bonked my head with a book every time I made a mistake.

De: Tell me who did that and I'll bonk him in the balls.

M: This is different because you really care about this topic. That's really what makes the difference between good and bad grades.

D: My world is upside down. 'N money's on the line.

De: And Congress is filled with swine.

D: Let's keep goin'.

De: You said the five star Amazon kind of ballot has two names. Which name applies to the kind of simple counting we've been talking about?

M: That kind of ballot is asking for a score or a rating. It's called a score ballot. It allows a voter to indicate how strongly the voter feels about who they like and dislike. Like the grades A through F.

De: Most politicians deserve an F, for ... fails to care about most voters.

D: We gotta grade them on a curve.

De: 'N that's why marking just the highest and lowest scores, is such a big deal?

M: Exactly! A plus again!

D: So how should we be countin' ballots? For elections. Where voters will try to increase their influence.

M: Before we move on to what I think is the best kind of vote counting, here's an interesting simple kind of improvement.

De: What's that?

M: Consider the same kind of ballot we use now, the single-mark ballot. But change the instructions and allow the voter to mark more than just one candidate. That's called approval voting.

De: Ah, because you either approve each candidate or leave their name unmarked.

D: This sounds like Facebook, where people can upvote anything and everything.

M: You're getting this!

De: On Reddit we can upvote and downvote. That's more info. Is that better?

M: Only if it's counted as three ranking levels.

D: Three?

M: Remember zero.

De: Ah, an upvote is like plus one. And a downvote is like minus one. And neither up nor down is like zero.

M: If counted right that could work. But using five levels collects more information than three. And when there are lots and lots of candidates then up to about twelve levels would work.

De: But not unlucky thirteen.

D: Since you brought it up, I'm guessing, approval voting might be fair?

M: It would work OK in primary elections because the winner would always be from the correct party.

De: But in general elections, the wrong party must not win. So there it would cause trouble, right?

M: Right. We need more than just one column of ballot ovals to avoid criticism of the results.

D: Wait a moment! Just changing written directions on the ballot would be an easy change to make, right?

M: I'm not politically savvy. That's outside my expertise. I just know the math behind ballot counting.

De: If we're gonna fight, let's get it right!

D: What's the best way to count votes?

M: You're finally ready to learn about ranking. It uses ranked ballots. They look the same as score ballots with ovals, but they're counted differently. It defeats the tactic of just marking the highest levels and lowest levels.

D: [Speaks to himself.] That's ranking.

M: How can those marks be counted in a way that holds up under scrutiny, without mutiny?

D: That's harder than any jigsaw puzzle I've ever seen.

M: Admittedly, if I asked this on a test I'd soon be under arrest. For cruel and gross cerebral punishment. [fix_humor] But guess anyway.

D: OK. Maybe ... we could start by looking at ... just the top part. The top-most candidate on each ballot. ...

M: Side step the fear and persevere.

D: And the candidate who gets the fewest top marks ... gets tossed aside?

De: Then the ballots are modified to hide the one dismissed. Then the process repeats. Until just one candidate remains?

M: That counting method has many different names. Here let's call it instant runoff voting. Among friends, or when a smartphone isn't handy, that method is dandy. It works well enough that it's been used in real elections. In fact it's used in Maine, and Australia, in San Francisco, and a few other places.

D: So I didn't guess right?

M: This is hard stuff. Not as hard as calculating the square root of your social security number on an abacus. You deserve another A plus. For the basic idea of using something besides counting marks and looking for the biggest count.

D: This is such a contrast to what in the past would have been a kick in the ass.

M: Yet this counting method is flawed. Instant runoff voting was used in the city of Burlington, in Vermont, and it failed. The candidate who won was not the one who deserved to win. We can do better. So which candidate should be the first to be eliminated?

D: I'm stumpified.

M: You've heard of the electoral college?

De: That's garbage!

M: Ah, but one thing it gets quite right. The winner of the electoral fight has to get more than half the votes.

De: More than half, that's called a majority.

M: If a candidate gets a majority, then vote splitting can't happen. That's so important that Roberts Rules of Order insist on majority support to declare a winner.

De: How do those rules say to count votes?

M: Those rules don't say how to get a majority. Just that it's necessary. They do say to not use what here we're calling instant runoff voting.

D: So getting more than half the votes is a must. But how can there always be a majority? Especially when there are more than two candidates?

M: Take a guess.

D: This is hard. Is it time for recess?

De: Remember that money is your reward for figuring this out.

M: In sports, how are teams ranked?

D: Aren't teams ranked based on, ... well, ... I think they get points, or maybe lose points, from each game.

M: How many teams compete in each game?

D: Just two.

M: And what's that called, two at a time?

D: I dunno.

De: Two at a time, that's a pair at a time.

M: Pairwise. That's the name. So how would that work?

D: Pairwise, ... ah, counting?

M: Yes, pairwise counting. It's a very important thing. How would that work?

D: It's counting, but it's beyond what my brain can handle without an assist from some Brainiac Elixer.

De: If it were sports teams, then, well, a team would be the worst if it lost all its pairwise matches.

M: Excellent! Keep going.

De: So the loser of all the pairwise contests would get eliminated.

D: 'N then we'd look for the next loser, from the remaining teams, er, candidates.

De: And when there's just one team, or candidate, remaining, that would be the winner, right?

M: Excellent! And the shortcut approach is to look for the candidate who wins all of their pairwise contests. The academic world calls that a Condorcet [pronounced cone-dor-SAY] winner.

De: Condorcet, that sounds stuffy.

M: It's named after a French guy whose title was the Marques de Condorcet. For a long time Europeans thought he was the first person to publish a description of that method.

De: I can see, as you say, the concept is the key. Yet on a test, students would be asked to recall, or recognize, his name. That's dumb.

D: I think I see. A Condorcet winner would get more than half the votes, a majority, without any vote splitting.

De: If this is such a great way to make selections, why isn't it used for elections?

M: Because sometimes there's no Condorcet winner. Using the elimination approach, it can reach a point where none of the candidates loses all its pairwise contests.

De: Partial losers. But no total losers.

D: Then what? Count how many loses? Or measure how big the loses are?

M: A plus for thinking of those ideas! Actually there are many ways to resolve those cases. Even better, there are methods that don't first look for Condorcet winners or losers. Instead they use the pairwise counts in ways that don't need to do anything special. Yet they find the Condorcet winner when one exists.

D: That sounds like magic.

M: It's beautiful advanced mathematics. After all, magic is a word for what we don't yet fully comprehend.

D: Like how my landlord calculates my utility bill.

De: Is there some method you like, that you could explain, in a way that makes that magic understandable?

M: Yes. But before that will make sense I should ask you how many pairwise counts are involved in each pairwise comparison.

D: I'll guess two. If the two candidates are named Pinoke and Oscar, there's the count for how many voters, well, support, uh, Pinoke over Oscar. And there's the other count, of how many voters prefer Oscar over Pinoke.

M: And will those two numbers always add up to the total number of voters?

D: I think so.

De: Ah, but what if some voters rank Pinoke and Oscar as equally acceptable?

D: Ah, that means there will be a third number. The number of voters who rank them as equally acceptable.

M: Excellent! Yes there are three numbers for each pairwise comparison. But when summarized, the third count can be omitted. This means the pairwise numbers can be put into a table, a square grid. And each row would be labelled with the name of a candidate. And the columns would be labelled with the same names in the same sequence. And each cell would contain a count.

De: So if the candidates are named Pinoke, Oscar, Barack, and Hypatia, it would be a four by four grid, right?

M: Indeed. Now you're ready to see the magic of the counting method I like best. It re-arranges the sequence of candidates, in the rows and columns. The goal is to re-arrange the sequence until the biggest pairwise counts move into the upper-right triangular area of the grid, and the smallest pairwise counts move into the other half, the lower-left triangular area. Then we look at that sequence. It indicates not only who is most popular, but who is second most popular, who is third most popular, and so on down to who is least popular.

De: What's that method called?

M: The Condorcet Kemeny method.

D: 'N is that the fairest method?

M: More research is needed to figure out which method is best.

D: I thought math was supposed to be precise. How can it be indecisive too?

De: Maybe that's the kind of math your landlord uses.

M: There's a mathematical proof that proves it's not possible for there to be a voting method that has no flaws.

De: So math doesn't have all the answers?

M: It's complicated.

De: Sounds like life and relationships.

M: There are some fairness characteristics, criteria, that voting methods pass or fail. Math geeks know which counting methods fail which criteria. But there has been no research to measure how often each method passes or fails each one.

D: Why hasn't that research been done?

M: Who would pay for a search to find the best replacement?

D: Whoever pays for research about dinosaurs.

De: And research in mathematics.

M: Most of that funding comes from the government. Of course the people who have power don't want to pay for research that reveals the unfairness that underpins their power.

De: A black widow spider's web of corruption!

D: I think we've learned what's needed. Ranked ballots and pairwise counting. So are we done?

M: There's more. So far we've been talking about how to choose a mayor, governor, or president with fairness. That's the first half. But what happens when there are lots of seats to fill, like in Congress?

D: Brain overload!

M: Oh right. Instead, try this. Imagine a group of friends choosing a second pizza topping for a pizza they will share. How would the second topping be chosen?

D: Couldn't the second-most popular candidate, er, topping, be elected, er, selected?

M: Second-most popular has more than one meaning. So let's try yet another metaphor. Imagine that five wolves and four sheep vote on what to eat for dinner.

De: Ha! The five wolves would eat the four sheep! And claim it's fair because it's democracy!

D: So us minorities, like the sheep, need a way to fight against a majority.

De: The Bill of Rights is nice, but that's not enough to protect us minorities from whites.

M: As you see, just getting a majority is not a fully zoomed out view.

D: I see somethin' else too. If districts were filled with wolves 'n sheep, 'n each district had slightly more wolves than sheep, then every district would elect a wolf. Then congress would be nothin' but wolves.

De: That's not far from what are now mostly white males.

M: In Europe, instead of wolves and sheep, they have a handful of political parties.

De: Like wolves and sheep and goats and pigs?

M: Sure. On the ballot each voter marks their favorite political party. Let's say lots of voters mark their ballot for the Pirate party.

D: I'd join that one. It sounds like they're against puppets.

De: Do they slash puppet strings with their swords?

M: They don't carry swords, or dress like pirates. But they do oppose what they think is corruption.

D: Go pirates!

M: In some European countries, adjustments are done to ensure the Pirate party, and every other party, gets their fair share of seats in parliament.

D: Does that work?

M: It hides the unfairness of still using single-mark ballots. Yet there are lots of people who like it. That's because they can point to someone in parliament and claim their vote helped elect that MP, er, member of parliament.

De: From reading news about Europe those governments have as much corruption as us.

M: Back to voting here in the United States, suppose each district filled two seats in the house of representatives.

De: That means districts would be twice the size of existing districts, right?

M: Very good!

D: OK, half as many districts, and two seats per district. Sounds slick.

M: Of course the most popular candidate wins the first seat.

De: So how's the second seat filled? In a way that's fair. For the sheep, and goats, and pigs? Or maybe I should say, for women to get the representation we deserve.

M: Using simple math, a computer can calculate which voters are well-represented by the first-seat winner.

D: Since that math is simple, I don't need to hear about it, right?

M: Right. The ballots of those well-represented voters would have their influence greatly reduced. Often all the way to zero. The remaining voters still have full influence for their ballots. Pairwise counting is done again, and the most popular candidate wins the second seat. In this district.

De: I'm guessing the effect would be to elect one Republican and one Democrat.

M: Typically yes, assuming both parties offer good candidates.

D: That means there would be more than just one Republican 'n one Democrat in the race?

M: Yes because vote splitting can't happen. So we need to allow for the possibility that one of the parties only offers disliked candidates, while the other party offers better candidates.

D: Ah, if, say, the Republican party only offered puppet candidates, like Pinoke 'n Oscar, 'n the Democratic party offered anti-corruption candidates, like Barack 'n Hypatia, then both winners could be Democrats?

M: Yes.

D: This seems like a winning pole vault over our low limbo bar, where we are now.

De: But if every district elects one Republican and one Democrat, then Congress would be tied. That's cockeyed. The population is not evenly divided between the two parties.

M: To fix that unfair balance, we make the districts a little bigger. And we reserve a few extra seats. Nationwide seats. Then we can do the party-based adjustment to figure out which party deserves to win each of those nationwide seats.

D: And the party leaders, like the insiders in the Pirate Party, would get to decide who should fill those seats? That seems not right. That would be unfair.

M: Lots of European nations do it that way. Yet you're right. It's not fair.

D: Why are those voters so stupid?

M: The people in power are the ones who have to approve any change.

De: I see. The members of parliament only embrace a change if it's likely to get themselves re-elected. Otherwise it would be as unlikely as turkeys voting in favor of Thanksgiving.

D: Another barrier!

M: Far fairer is to look at the ballots again to identify the most popular of the un-elected candidates. The most popular such candidate from the correct party would fill that party's extra seat. Then the process gets repeated.

De: That sounds like it would rip control away from party insiders. And empower the voters.

D: That seems much much fairer than what we've got now.

M: With no vote splitting, general elections would no longer be limited to just one candidate per party.

De: That means there could be lots more candidates, right?

M: That's right.

D: Desha you're bright.

De: It's just counting.

M: And that's what the important parts of mathematics are mostly about, counting.

D: So how can the ballot handle lots of candidates?

M: A separate ballot question can ask voters to rank the political parties. That gives us the info we need to calculate the popularity of the parties.

D: Voting for parties? Is that really a thing?

M: That's what lots of people in lots of nations do on their ballots. Using that info, the most popular parties can be allowed to have two or three of their candidates in each race.

D: And the least popular parties get excluded?

M: That makes sense to me.

D: And the biggest third parties get one candidate each, right?

M: That gives small parties an opportunity to grow. And even to overtake big parties.

D: I don't like names, but this is getting complex. Is there a name for all of this mess?

M: It is sort of like a jigsaw puzzle with lots of pieces, and different pieces would work, and they have lots of names. But the only method that does all of what I've described under a single name is called VoteFair Ranking.

De: VoteFair?

D: FairVote?

M: VoteFair is the ranking method I like. FairVote is an organization that promotes instant runoff voting and something called the single transferable vote. They call those methods ranked choice voting.

De: That's confusing.

M: Yes, intentionally.

D: OK, you like VoteFair something. Is there a less-specific name?

M: Pairwise vote counting. That's the most important part. Because pairwise counts reveal not just support but opposition.

D: So it's ranked ballots and pairwise vote counting that you recommend?

M: Plus adjustments we've discussed that give fuller representation.

De: To the sheep and goats and pigs defending themselves against the wolves.

D: So how hard's it to do pairwise counting?

M: All the counting is done by computer, so a tap on the screen is all that's needed.

De: So what's the barrier against using ranked ballots and pairwise counting?

M: Up until a few decades ago, when computers came along, doing the math by hand was the big barrier.

D: But now we have computers, so what's stopping us now?

M: Fear. Especially a fear of math. Officially that's called mathematical anxiety. Lots of people have it 'cause many people don't trust what they don't understand.

D: Math anxiety. That's what I was infected by.

De: And, the biggest campaign contributors don't want anyone to cut the puppet strings they use to control politicians. And their minions, the insiders within the two political parties, don't want to get fired. Or lose their perks.

D: Why isn't the benefit of greater fairness attracting voters like a magnet?

De: You are so naïve. Greedy folks don't want fairness.

D: Those of us who are sufferin' want our fair share of the economic pie.

De: And rich people want to protect their too-big slice of economic pie, probably with vanilla ice cream and three cherries on top.

M: Speaking of that, here are colored blocks that represent nine ballots, and the colors represent ice cream flavors.

De: Pretty colors! Which flavors?

M: Dark brown is chocolate.

De: Yum!

M: Pink is for strawberry.

De: I'm not a fan of pink.

M: This color represents mint chocolate chip.

De: And I presume the last color is vanilla.

M: Right.

De: But you haven't explained why you're pointing out these colored blocks.

M: With these ballot preferences the winning flavor can be mint chocolate chip, or strawberry, or vanilla, depending on which counting method is used.

D: Ah, so the counting method does matter!

M: Definitely. And yet, almost any method is better than what we've got now.

D: If elections were fair, what would change, politically?

De: Yeah, especially for the unfortunate poor. And us college grads who failed to get to the middle class.

M: The answer to that I don't know. For that you need to ask someone who understands both economics and game theory.

D: Game theory?

M: It's an academic field that studies, well, it's difficult to describe. But it includes vote counting. I do know someone with those credentials. But he's at a university that's a four-hour drive away.

D: Do you think he'd give us a peek into that future?

M: I can ask him by email.

D: That'd be super!

M: He studies, and teaches about, economic history.

D: Oh I do hate history. As much as I did mathematics. 'N economics, that's more math.

M: This professor can make history fun.

D: Can that be done?

M: You did great with mathematics. As for math in economics, it's just different names for money. Like tax, debt, interest, tariffs, and bribes.

D: I'm a dummy but I'll try.

M: One more tip. There's something called mathiness. It's a misuse of mathematics. Math doesn't lie, but some liars use numbers when they lie.

D: Mathiness must be what my landlord's usin' on me.

De: I admit I tend to distrust math until I do the counting or calculations myself.

D: So, we've learned that ranked ballots and pairwise vote counting is the key to less corruption in Washington DC. But do we need to remember that guy's name? Condolences, or something?

M: Pairwise vote counting includes Condorcet methods, and some non-Condorcet methods. So just remember the concept of pairwise vote counting. And needing more than half those votes.

D: Half's a fraction I can recall. But I don't understand why you made a big deal out of the digit zero.

M: It took our ancestors hundreds of years to make the leap from the number zero to the digit zero. To us, in hindsight, that's slow. In a similar way folks in the distant future will marvel that it took so long for us to use pairwise counting for counting votes. Zero as a digit changed the world in marvellous ways. Similarly pairwise vote counting will change the world in marvellous ways.

D: So just like we don't know what we've got til it's gone, we don't really know what's missing until it can be seen in hindsight?

De: I was right. You are very bright.

M: That's a wise insight.

D: That's just common sense. But what you've taught us are hidden secrets. The ones those greedy ... business owners ... don't want us to find out. We're grateful for your valuable insights. We'll share them.

M: Remember your promise, ... that you won't reveal where they came from.

D: OK, but why?

M: I've got tenure, so I'm not likely to lose my job. But I can lose grants for my research projects.

D: Ah, 'n some of your funds come from the government, right?

M: Yes. Lots.

De: When we bite the hand that feeds you we won't reveal who took us off our leashes.

D: We can say we learned it from Wikipedia.

M: Only bits of it are in Wikipedia. That's because they require academic references, especially for mathematical topics.

De: And I suppose those references don't exist because governments don't fund such research.

D: This is all seeming like a giant conspiracy, except that it's in plain view.

De: It's hidden behind the curtain of mathematics, under the unmarked trap door of pairwise vote counting.

D: Fear of math keeps it well hidden.

De: This makes it all the more special that you've taken the time to explain this to us.

D: I'm extremely grateful. You've given me, us, more than I could ever have hoped for.

M: I love these kinds of conversations. I wish textbooks and those dang standardized tests would allow me to teach more like this, without as much notation and terminology. The joy of math is in the concepts. That's what counts.

D: I think I'm beginning to see a fraction of that joy in mathematics.

De: Ah, one more thing. Since pairwise counting is a few years off, what can we do in this election to fight against vote splitting?

M: Tell your friends, including the ones online, that current ballots are not asking who is your favorite? And if they want to say none of the above, then marking a can't-win name is not the way to say that. And not voting does not express none of the above. The way to defeat vote splitting is to vote in both primary and general elections. And especially voters need to hold their nose and mark a candidate who has a chance of winning. Otherwise they weaken the candidate they prefer.

De: But that means never voting for a third-party candidate, right?

M: No. You can vote for a third-party candidate if the candidate you most despise will easily win. Except in the case of presidential elections. For those the popular vote still matters. That's because the gap between winner 'n loser is put under a microscope.

D: What's the best way to express none of the above?

M: That choice doesn't fit on a ballot. That's why the first amendment exists. That means you get to express your opinions by promoting podcasts and Facebook posts you like.

De: And protest signs! Plus, I suppose when there's enough support, Jon Oliver will tells us why we're stupid not to have been using pairwise vote counting.

D: You're a true guru.

De: Thank you! All of this has been so helpful.

D: Yes, thank you! Especially, thanks for teaching me I'm not a third-wit loser.

De: With what we've learned, we're ready to attack and burn up our enemy, the people who are corrupt.

Scene 6, Economic Engines

De (Desha): [Desha and Damien enter classroom.] Are you professor Pengaritihas?

P (Pengaritihas): Yes. Are you two Demon and Dasha?

De: I'm Desha.

D (Damien): I'm Damien.

P: Welcome to my classroom. Would you like some pistachios?

D: I'm so full of nuts I could get a dozen squirrels through winter.

De: We're wired on espresso. So let's go!

D: I'm hungry to learn.

De: We came to learn the dark arts of economics. Please tell us what will happen when elections are fair.

D: When vote splittin's no longer skewing the outcome.

P: It's not goat spitting. It's vote splitting.

D: We know it's super challengin' to predict the future.

P: That's mostly what us economists are paid to do. Predict the future.

D: Are they, well you too, in hindsight, usually right?

P: Sometimes yes, and then we modestly say I told you so. Sometimes no, and then we apply for a research grant to study why we were wrong.

De: So you get paid more if you're wrong? Are economists wealthy?

D: Desha, your espresso is showing. Professor, do you have a general notion 'bout what will change? Especially in Washington.

P: Lots of laws will be passed. Then a few people who greatly profit from existing conditions will earn less money, and almost everyone else will enjoy increased prosperity.

De: What's your justification? For that prediction?

P: That trend has been going on throughout civilization and history. Not counting setbacks caused by warfare.

D: Can you explain why?

P: Imagine the economy as a strawberry pie.

De: I'm not fond of strawberry pie. Can we call it a cherry pie?

P: Of course. Now imagine the economy is a cherry pie. If some people cut themselves a slice that is too big, then other people end up with smaller slices.

D: I'm following this. Wow!

P: What would you like to call the people who take too big of a slice?

D: People in the political down. As opposed to the political left 'n political right.

De: 'N the people who get too little would be people in the political up.

P: Clearly you've got your bearings in the political jungle. So, the way I see it, fairer elections would yield elected leaders who care more about the people you call the political up. Currently those people get too little economic pie. So of course replacement politicians would pass laws that give bigger slices of economic pie to the majority of voters.

D: So far this is easier than playing air guitar.

De: When I took economics one oh one, it wasn't this fun.

P: We'll get to the complicated bit soon, and that involves a bit of history.

D: Oh dear, not silly, wonky history. I learned some. But what's the past got to do with anything? Other than playing trivia games. And using history tests to expose who's a dummy.

P: Imagine that walking backwards [walks backward] is like moving forward in time. [points over shoulder] The future I cannot see [points straight ahead] so I peer into the past. That gives me clues about where we're headed. So it's like a crystal ball. History allows us to see that which is yet to be.

D: Wow! History is about the future. Who knew?

P: Many people mistakenly believe that history is recalling facts about the past.

D: In a history trivia contest Wikipedia would beat me like the loudest drum in a marchin' band.

P: Reading Wikipedia would be a great way to learn history.

D: My eyes are cryin' just thinkin' about reading Wikipedia so much.

De: You said that reading glasses with a blue tint helps with books. You can change Wikipedia's white background to blue on a browser.

D: I'll give that trick a try.

P: What's really much more interesting about history, rather than facts, is causation. Cause and effect. And unintended consequences.

D: Can ya toss me an example?

P: Here's an example that involves snakes.

De: The political kind?

P: Cobras.

De: I like them, at a distance.

P: A city in India had a problem with lots of cobra snakes, so they put a bounty on the snakes.

D: I recognize bounty as another word for money.

P: So how would you expect that to turn out?

De: Fewer cobra snakes.

D: Since you're usin' it as an example, I'll guess the number of snakes increased.

P: Indeed, the cobra population increased. So the test question is: why?

D: I hate tests. My brain freezes.

P: Flunk! With your brain, try to maintain your focus on the topic, the subject, the concept. Don't try to push away the fear. Instead let go of the fear. It shouldn't be a struggle. Just un-cling to the emotion. That cuts the umbilical connection. Let go of fear.

D: Got it. I'll focus on the topic of snakes. There's less fear there.

De: So why did the cobra population increase?

P: When money gets offered for something then people do what it takes to get that money. Enterprising city residents went into the cobra snake breeding business.

D: I'll guess that after realizing what was going on, the bounty was ended and those extra snakes got released?

P: A plus! That's what happened. This historical event reminds us to consider otherwise unexpected consequences.

De: There are lots of awful unfair consequences of Congress and its corruption, but those shouldn't be unexpected.

P: Let's look at one of the problems that economists face. You've heard of the gross domestic product, the GDP?

D: Yeah, it measures, well, when it goes up, that's good. 'N when it goes down, that's bad.

P: So here's the next test question. Does the GDP go up or down when a family's house burns down?

D: This seems like another trick question so I'll say GDP goes up.

P: C plus. For an A you need to tell me why.

De: Because building the replacement house, or more likely the selling of the property to a developer who builds a condominium, is business activity, and that's what GDP measures.

P: A plus. Yes, GDP just measures transfers of money. When nothing is bought or sold there's no change in gross domestic product.

D: That is gross. But what's this got to do with election vote-counting reform?

P: When people are optimistic about the future, GDP goes up because people buy more products, pay for more services, eat out, and make babies. But when people are pessimistic about the future, they fearfully cling to their money, so there are fewer transfers of money. And when they postpone making babies, there are fewer future customers. All that pulls down GDP.

De: N' you think people will become optimistic when fairer voting methods are adopted?

P: The short answer is yes. The fuller answer involves what's happening now in the economy.

D: I keep hearing the economy's on the climbing path of a roller coaster. But I'm in a car that's derailed and I'm plunging fast.

P: The stock market keeps going up and up because people with money have few other places to invest it. Specifically certificates of deposit don't yield much interest.

D: That gives the stock market sort of a monopoly.

De: So stocks are like an over-inflated balloon. Does that mean our roller coaster ride will soon plummet? And the poor will all die?

P: It's difficult to predict when it will drop from its recent top.

D: You said economists predict the future.

P: Knowing what will happen is different from knowing when those whats will happen. Professors of economics focus on rational behavior. But successful investors earn lots of money by knowing the stock market can stay irrational longer than investors can stay solvent.

De: Fortune tellers who teach?

P: We develop math proofs yet we're guilty of some goofs.

D: Why doesn't the economy work for me, even though the numbers say everything's hunky dory? Is this an example of mathiness?

P: I don't know what mathiness is. But numbers can be deceptive. What many people overlook is that the unemployment rate that's in the news just counts people who are now getting unemployment benefits.

De: Those benefits run out after a few months of having no job. I've learned that from experience. So unemployment is actually higher, right?

P: Yes, it's higher.

D: Why don't economists measure that? The real unemployment rate.

P: The government does measure that unemployment rate as well. But most newspapers and TV stations report the one that government officials call attention to.

D: So the government's being sneaky, right?

P: The government knows that if they call attention to the higher unemployment rate, then all that optimism disappears. Then the economy and the GDP would trend downward. And that would activate a bad feedback loop.

D: What's a weed black poop?

P: A feedback loop. When you're in an auditorium and the sound system squeals, that's a feedback loop.

D: Oh yeah. That's when a tiny sound at the microphone gets amplified 'n comes out the speakers 'n gets back to the microphone just slightly louder than before.

P: It becomes as loud as possible as fast as possible. And a feeback loop is what makes a hurricane so powerful. There are lots of feedback loops. That's what's behind economic inflation.

D: A strong wind?

P: When an employee who makes plush toy dinosaurs gets a raise, the business raises the price of their dinos. A mother working in a grocery store then gets a raise to afford rising toy prices. Then the grocery store slightly raises its prices to cover that salary increase. Then that feeds back to the original employee who shops at that grocery store.

De: That's inflation, when salaries and prices increase together.

P: That feedback loop has to be slowed down by doing something that decouples at least one of the links in the loop.

D: So announcing a higher rate of unemployment would undermine optimism. And that would bring down the economy. And that would cause more layoffs, which speeds up how fast the economy goes down. This makes sense.

De: Governments try to make the economy grow. But without allowing inflation to inflate too fast.

P: That's the concept. Of course my students have to say it academically correctly.

D: Otherwise they'd get bad grades on standardized tests, right?

P: Alas, yes. I have to teach to the tests. Yet the important parts of economics are the concepts, and that's why it's a delight to get to explain them to you two.

D: [Faces Desha] So here the concept is, ... your poop scooper loop's a feedback loop?

De: That's different. Dog owners have to care about the health of other dogs to protect their own dog's health. Here, in economic kinds of feedback loops, self-interest is the motivation.

D: Ah, the employees ask for a higher salary for selfish reasons. 'N the business owner sells at higher prices for selfish reasons.

P: Right. In economic feedback loops the changes happen because each person focuses on what they themselves want. Without caring about what others want. Like with those cobra snake breeders. They didn't much care how many cobra snakes are in the city. Their actions were just based on monetary self-interest.

D: I see. Dog owners, the pooper scooper ones, care how many piles of dog poop their dog can sniff. But that's affected by other dog owners. There's no benefit to poop scooping if other dog owners don't scoop too.

De: You've got it.

D: Hey! Wait a moment. Feedback loops are what rich business owners use to get oversized slices of economic pie. They use lawyers. And they control news sources. And they control politicians. Those loops make them wealthier and wealthier.

De: And the rest of us can't afford to buy even a slice of strawberry, er, cherry pie. Yet why does it seem that rent 'n food 'n ice cream are going up and up fast while salaries stay stuck?

P: It's not your imagination. The cost of living is going up faster than the consumer price index, which is the official measurement of inflation.

De: That's probably another corrupt measurement. But I forgot why it's corrupt.

P: You didn't forget. We can't teach why to undergrads. Part of the why is because back when the price of food items were quickly rising, some food items were replaced by items whose cost were declining.

D: What's declining in cost?

P: The per-pixel cost of digital cameras.

D: I recognize that word per. It means division. And the number of pixels in a camera are going up, so dividing by that bigger number makes the result go down.

De: So that's another way the government is hiding the real cost of living. I can guess why they're not being transparent. But something else is going on, right?

P: Yes. Some government expenses are matched to the consumer price index. Such as retirement pensions for government employees, and social security benefits. And that index's linked to the interest they pay for borrowed money. So the government wants inflation to stay low.

D: So the government saves lots of money by pretending inflation is low, right?

P: Yes. And as another trick they get to exclude rent and fuel, which are rising quickly. They're excluded from that index because they're too volatile.

De: That means they go up and down like a nervous kangaroo rat.

D: Is anything else being fudged? Besides hot sundaes.

P: Desha, do you remember from econ one oh one what determines interest rates?

De: The federal reserve chooses when to increase and decrease the interest rate, right?

P: That's the rate talked about in the news, but more important is the rate determined by auctioning treasuries.

De: I don't remember learning about those actions, I mean, auctions.

P: It's not taught to undergrads.

De: I'll bet textbooks don't include it because schools are funded by the government. So textbooks can't reveal secrets the government wants to hide.

P: Yes, that's another feedback loop.

D: All these feedback loops! They make math seem simple.

De: I agree.

P: U.S. treasuries are sold in auctions. In economically optimistic times they sell for higher prices, closer to the amount the government pays when they reach their redemption date.

De: Ah, but in economically pessimistic times the buyers pay much less. That increases the gap between purchase price and redemption payment. So that brings up rates of interest, right?

D: Ah, I think I'm following. Since interest rates are low, that means there's lots of buyers for those treasuries?

P: A plus. Yes, normally. But China and Russia stopped buying them so lately the federal reserve has been buying lots of them.

De: That would be like the plush toy dinosaur business buying its own dinos to give the appearance of extra customers and income.

P: That's partly why the deficit is so huge.

D: Ah, so the U.S. government has increased its debt to compensate for rough times economically?

De: Wait a moment. Our economy's like a stack of wood blocks in a teetering tower that's ready to fall?

P: Almost all nations and all big businesses are in debt. So are farmers. They all have to borrow first before they can grow crops or manufacture or whatever to get income.

De: So being in debt is not a big deal, but a growing deficit, that's bad, right?

P: Relatively speaking, yes. But as long as the government is keeping its citizens happy, and happier than in other nations, problems can be hidden behind curtains of distraction.

De: The number of people trying to immigrate into the U.S. is still high, right? So that suggests success. Yet things are a mess.

D: So what should be going on instead?

P: History tells us that prosperity happens when a city, nation, or region sells something that people outside the region either need or strongly desire. And it's not available from anywhere else.

D: An example would help.

P: Do you know what the silk road was?

D: Yeah, Marco Polo and lots of caravans traveled along it to get silk from China.

De: That means China was getting lots of valuable things flowing into their country to pay for the silk.

D: So that made China rich.

P: China wisely kept their special silkworms within the Forbidden City to protect their monopoly. Protecting a monopoly through secrecy is an important way for a region or a business to dramatically gain economic prosperity.

De: The Forbidden City's the fortress where the emperor of China lived.

D: Be the only source of something valuable. That's a monopoly. Hmm, this seems familiar.

P: Another way to increase prosperity is to increase efficiency.

D: I need an example again.

P: Consider the Roman empire. They wrote laws to control business and commerce, including setting standards for weights and sizes. And they used soldiers and courts to enforce those laws. And they built roads and patroled them with soldiers. They built aqueducts to channel water to cities. All of that greatly increased the efficiency of their economy.

D: Huh? Economic efficiency?

P: Economic efficiency means something different. Here I'm talking about efficiency as a general concept, where profits go up when costs go down. And costs go down when people spend less time fetching water, getting cheated as a customer, breaking cart wheels on bad roads, getting robbed, and getting sick because of not having water to wash their hands.

D: Less time wasted. Got it.

P: Especially important is for there to be less fighting. Not only physical fighting, but fewer business disputes.

D: Since efficiency is so important, economists measure it, right?

De: They think they do. They have something called economic efficiency, but that's more like the gain and loss of a cherry pie. And they have something called the productivity index. But it's flawed.

P: A plus. You do remember some economics. The productivity index is supposed to measure productivity, which is similar to efficiency. Yet that index increases when a house burns down and then inexpensively gets rebuilt. Of course it would be even more efficient if the house never burned down. But measuring non-destruction, alas that's not a sexy topic that attracts economists' attention.

D: So if efficiency is what made the Roman empire great, why did it decline? In just a sentence or two.

De: If all the books on this subject fell on you, you'd get buried in an avalanche ten feet high.

P: I'll give you just the relevant part. After the years of good governance, when things were prosperous, corruption grew. And corruption reduces efficiency.

D: Why?

De: This is going to take awhile. What I'm wearing might go out of style.

P: Actually it's simple. You know what the free market is, right?

D: Yeah.

De: Of course.

P: In an ideal free market, there are no barriers. People can choose what to buy, what to sell, how much to charge, and whatever else, without fighting. That's a fluid, flexible, and efficient, economy. But corruption? That puts up barriers that are chosen to channel money into specific pockets. Those corrupt barriers reduce efficiency.

D: I think I've got it. Efficiency and selling what's desirable is what brings money into a region. And corruption reduces efficiency, which causes economic decline.

De: In ancient Rome a bigger source of wealth was through conquest. That means stealing. That's what brought lots of wealth into Rome, from other regions.

D: But that ends when there's no more regions to conquer, right?

P: Yes. Basically that's the kids' book version of the Roman empire. A similar kind of rise and fall pattern happened later with the Italian Renaissance. It started with efficient banking. Plus improved ships using technology from China.

De: The compass, right?

P: And the ship's rudder.

D: And the digit zero.

P: You're astute!

D: No my ass didn't toot!

De: Astute. It means your brain just did the equivalent of a gymnastics triple twist vault with a perfect landing.

D: Oh thanks! And gunpowder too?

P: Certainly gunpowder enabled seagoing people to exploit other regions and their resources.

De: Now that I better understand that transporting silk and other stuff ...

P: Gold, ivory, frankincense, and sweet exotic candy. [OK as is? fix_humor]

De: ... between Asia and Europe was what big ships were being used for, I realize that running into America and taking land from the natives, and enslaving Africans to work on plantations in the Caribbean, was a bonus. And giving religious folks a place where they could escape competing religions was just, for us, a lucky byproduct?

P: Basically, yes. And it gave democracy a place to grow, far away from big armies and navies. The resulting cooperation among U.S. states led to immense prosperity. That's why a couple centuries later Europeans formed the European Union. That's an effort to copy the cooperation that works so well in the United States. Europeans finally set aside their religious differences, their cultural differences, and their language differences.

De: You said fighting undermines the economy. Yet political hawks, who are mostly conservatives, promote warfare as a way to increase prosperity. And competition between businesses is the basis of prosperity in a free market, right?

D: I'm lost. I feel like I'm in a maze and someone turned off the lights.

P: Competition between businesses provides motivation to work hard. But what gets overlooked is the teamwork, the cooperation, among employees within the same business.

D: Huh?

De: Ah, employees getting along, who wouldn't normally get along. Like employees ignoring racial differences, religious differences, and gender differences.

D: Ah, and Republicans and Democrats ignoring their differences while at work.

De: When these conflicts are ignored, that's cooperation. Ah, that increases efficiency within the business.

D: So cooperation within a business makes the business strong, so it can better compete against other businesses? The lights are coming back on. I think I see.

De: So fighting between groups of people inspires, motivates, cooperation within each group?

P: That's not a bad simplification.

D: So a free market is a good thing?

P: A fully free market is impossible, yet it gets tried repeatedly, and it fails. Like the Articles of Confederation.

D: What's that?

De: Basically the U.S. Constitution is version two point oh. The Articles of Confederation was version one point oh.

P: It failed partly because it asked each colony to supply soldiers and weapons and such, but there was no negative consequence for the colonies that didn't. So the Constitution, among other changes, taxed the colonies to pay for one big army and navy. That cooperation was the opposite of what European nations were doing, which was fighting each other endlessly.

De: So you're saying that if there was a fully free market then we wouldn't have things like a military?

P: Or public schools, food for the poor, hospitals, or orphanages for little orphan Annies. Those things were created by churches, and promoted by religions.

D: Religion?

P: Ancient priests in Egypt earned their grain and beer by predicting eclipses so their boss, the pharaoh, could pretend to be powerful. And they predicted when the Nile River would flood and recede. Plus each year priests used mathematics and surveying to lay out the new farming boundaries. All of that was like magic to people who didn't understand astronomy, weather, and geometry.

De: That's why Galileo was a threat to the Catholic Church. He showed that science was better than priests at those things.

P: And priests lost lots of credibility, plus their lives, during the European black death by praying for the dying.

De: And by failing to cure the sick. With prayers, holy water, and advising pilgrims to kneel before the pelvic bone of Saint Bernard of Biddlesbourough. [OK as-is? fix_humor]

P: So lots of what was once done by religion has split into science, engineering, public education, and government. Now, as I see it, the big barrier against progress for civilization is our use of very primitive voting methods.

D: So what would happen if we, the majority of voters, could elect leaders who care? How would those leaders change the U.S. economy? To make it fair. I assume they would increase our efficiency, right?

P: Yes they would want to increase prosperity. As a start, they would avoid making big mistakes other nations have made.

De: An example?

P: When England was prosperous they raised tariffs as a way to increase their income, or so they thought. But higher tariffs, just like higher prices, only work if there's a monopoly. That new barrier gave Dutch people a trading advantage, because they had lower tariffs.

De: So higher tariffs on English goods motivated other nations to trade with the Dutch instead of the English? Isn't that when Dutch business owners grew so wealthy they bid up the price of tulip bulbs to sub-orbital highs?

P: Indeed.

De: And isn't that when the Pilgrims moved to Holland, where the Dutch live, so they could escape religious persecution from the state-run church in England?

P: Right.

D: If free markets are great, why don't we have more of that? 'N fewer monopolies?

De: Great question.

P: A free market saves money for lots of people. But it decreases income for people who cling to outdated ways of doing business. So naturally wealthy business owners pay politicians to keep the status quo.

De: Status quo ...

D: Means keepin' things as they are. I've been doing some cramming.

P: On the flip side, a free market increases wealth for people who innovate instead of cling.

D: Is this why Amazon does so well? And why retail stores are suffering? Amazon uses computers to replace the inefficiency of people.

De: I've worked in retail stores. Talk about inefficiency. I had to count out change when someone handed me cash. And countless customers interrupted me because they were too lazy to read the huge sign with an arrow that said restrooms.

D: And looking at the city level, driving to stores wastes lots of time and fuel, right?

P: You're getting this! Congratulations.

De: Here in the U.S. we have to buy sugar that's made from crops grown domestically. So that means we're wasting lots of money that could be spent on other things if we bought our sugar from outside the U.S., right? So we should eliminate monopolies, right?

P: Monopolies do reduce this kind of efficiency. But some monopolies are needed, such as for making strategic things. Like bombs, anti-viral face masks, and Pixar movies. Decades ago sugar was regarded as a strategic advantage. That's why it's got a monopoly.

De: Getting fat is a strategic advantage?

P: My expertise is in economics. I don't claim to be an expert about military defensibility, or preparing for pandemics, power-grid failures, and earth's orgasms. [fix_humor, joke OK as-is?]

D: So goods and services should be used wisely. And shouldn't be wasted. That makes sense.

P: There's something else that shouldn't be wasted. It's difficult to measure, so it's easily overlooked. Consider what happened in Britain during World War One. It was popular for university-educated men to volunteer to fight in that war.

De: They got slaughtered in the trenches. Lots of knowledge and lots of skills died with them. What a waste.

P: And that caused a bad feedback loop. It reduced the people who could educate the next generation.

D: Ah, so that's why men in college get excluded when there's a military draft. I see. Knowledge and skills are also resources that can get used wisely or wasted.

P: Or lost. During the European black death, lots of blacksmiths and ship builders and court jesters died. With them died lots of valuable knowledge.

De: Jesters knew how to juggle pig bladders and chew berries at the same time?

P: Back before the iPod and Netflix and radio and even record players, music and jokes and dances could only be heard or seen in the presence of musicians, storytellers, dancers, and jesters. If they died without passing along what they knew, their sweet songs, spellbinding stories, tantalizing dances, and hilarious jokes got lost.

De: Ah, death. It takes so much away.

P: In those times swords, and horseshoes, and sailing ships were high technology. That's why blacksmiths and ship builders were so valuable.

De: Is this related to why humans haven't recently walked on the moon? Losing knowledge?

P: Alas, yes. The people who knew how to put them there are dead, or retired. The opposite of losing knowledge is gaining knowledge. That's what gave strength to the Islamic Golden Age.

D: What's that?

De: That's when Bagdad was the center of an empire of people who spoke Arabic and followed the religion of Islam. A wise ruler, whose name I don't remember ...

P: ... Harun al-Rashid, at the end of the seven hundreds ...

De: ... collected books and gathered wise scholars from around the world, and paid smart people to develop things like algebra, geometry, and ..., I forget what else.

P: Three D drawings, robotic mechanisms, and much more.

D: Is that when the digit zero made its way closer to Europe?

De: Yes, and why Europeans and we refer to the digits zero through nine as Arabic numerals.

P: A plus plus. And that empire became weak as a result of what?

D: Corruption I'll bet.

P: Yes, including a dismissal of science.

De: People who dismiss science are doubly stupid. And I'll bet some of them are capitalists who fail to see that the loss of science leads the economy into a death spiral.

D: Another bad feedback loop. Got it. About stupidity, how come it so often wins against knowledge?

P: Dictators and wannabe dictators like to be in control. But they fail to realize that economic prosperity rests on the shoulders of the smart. When Mao Zedong led China he banished intellectuals to manual-labor jobs. That undermined the economy. After Mao died the brightest compliant ones were allowed back into science and business, and that shift paid off.

De: Did earlier Chinese rulers do better?

D: Chinese emperors feared losing what they called the mandate of heaven. What we call the right to rule. Especially they feared natural disasters. That's because too many deaths caused by flood, or pandemic, or crop failure, led to rebellion and revolution.

D: Too bad those signs are ignored by Congress and U.S. voters.

P: Another big loss of efficiency is mismanagement. That's partly why NASA lost its ability to make rockets that can take astronauts to the space station.

De: And why now NASA has to buy passage for astronauts on Russian rockets.

P: On the topic of Russia, socialism is what some folks think would be better than capitalism, but it's not.

De: I learned that once. But when I try to remember why, what comes up is something about chocolate.

P: It's because free markets more quickly arrive at the most efficient networks and interdependencies. In contrast, socialism attempts to control markets from the top down, using quotas, and penalties, and fixing prices, such as the price of sugar. But those rules can't change as fast as what happens at the bottom of the economy. Plus they do hiring and firing based on nepotism and favoritism, not competence.

D: What's nepo... whatever.

De: Hiring family members.

D: So let me see if I'm understanding. ... A free and efficient market's like letting water find its own way to the ocean? Instead of trying to redirect rivers. Is that right?

P: That's a useful metaphor. Now, finally, you're ready to understand something important that doesn't have a name.

De: Bring it on!

P: A very effective way for an existing government to increase prosperity is to increase taxes on business activities that are wasteful or inefficient. And to decrease taxes on business activities that are efficient and bring a net flow of money into the region. In this case the region is the U.S.

D: So which business activities are which?

P: Let's consider some different kinds of businesses. How about farming?

D: That brings money in. If the crops are sold outside the U.S.

P: Which is part of why farmers get lots of special government subsidies. How about manufacturing?

D: That brings money in, when the products are sold outside the U.S.

De: I thought that manufacturing businesses were bad.

P: Back when the industrial revolution began, that was common. And still there are some businesses that treat laws as if they're optional suggested guidelines. But today's transgressions are mild compared to earlier times.

D: A manufacturing business doesn't need to be bad. Got it.

P: If there were lower taxes for good manufacturing businesses, that would reward them for efficiently hiring skilled workers who transform raw materials into valuable products worth lots of money.

De: So software businesses would get lower taxes too? They bring lots of money into the United States from other nations, and they just consume electricity. And they hire highly skilled software developers.

P: Great example. How about mining companies?

D: They bring lots of money into the U.S.

De: But the U.S. loses lots of natural resources that future generations will come to miss, right?

P: Yes. Like Japan, where they cut down their forests for firewood. Now they buy lots of timber from the U.S. Or did back when massive logging was done in the Pacific Northwest.

D: So mining and timber businesses deserve to pay higher taxes, right?

P: The word deserve is judgemental, so that's a matter of opinion. There might be times when Desha thinks you deserve to be spanked with a wet towel, but that would be a judgement, not a fact.

De: In this case it's a fact.

P: But, yes, if mining and timber industries export lots of materials now, then future generations will not have those resources to use, sell, or waste.

De: Short-sighted capitalists. Speaking of that, what's capitalism? It's confusing to me.

P: That's because the word really has different meanings in different situations. Of course textbooks carefully define it, but those definitions use words that don't fully capture exactly what it means every time it's used.

De: Which explains why so much of what I learned in school now seems like snow on a sunny hillside. It's long gone. But this, what you're teaching us, reveals so many secrets that lie beneath puzzling mysteries, of why things are the way they are. So I think I'll remember most of it for a long time.

P: It's a joy to really get to teach what's important! Now, back to what doesn't have an official name. How about artists, writers, composers, and other people who create things that can be sold for way more than the cost of electricity and art supplies and creative software?

D: Clearly they deserve, er, should get, lower taxes on their businesses.

De: So what's this called? This thing of imposing lower taxes on businesses that efficiently create things of value. And imposing higher taxes on businesses that waste resources.

D: Or don't attract as much money into the United States.

P: It's an idea still in its infancy. So it doesn't have an established name. I've only heard it called tax the takers more than the makers.

D: I like that. People like me who wanna make things would earn higher wages because of those lower taxes.

De: And corporations would pay much higher taxes.

P: Only some corporations would pay higher taxes. Other corporations create lots of valuable products and services, and they would pay lower taxes.

De: Which corporations create value? I thought that big corporations are predatory.

P: The Corporation For Public Broadcasting creates lots of great educational TV shows for kids.

D: And for adults. Their NOVA shows are great.

De: That's cheating. That's a corporation that's not profit-focused.

P: Admittedly big corporations do tend to be greedy. And lots of them, especially insurance companies, get most of their income from within the U.S. Yet when they were young and small, Google and Facebook and even Bank of America benefitted lots of people without being so greedy. And there are some decent big businesses such as Ben and Jerry's, and relatively speaking, Apple. More importantly for this discussion there are lots of small corporations you've never heard of that benefit lots of people in lots of wonderful ways.

De: Ah, I suppose it's like with rich people. Some are good, and some are bad. I have to pay attention to what they do.

P: Indeed. And I'll say I'm glad you see that simply taxing wealthy individuals isn't the key.

D: I learned they can hide Florida condos, showy yachts, and Tesla SUVs in the businesses n' trusts they own. So they can evade individual taxation. 'N exploit tax deductions in their businesses.

P: And it's harder to figure out which rich folks deserve to be wealthy.

De: None of them!

P: Can you not think of any wealthy people who deserve to earn lots of money for their work?

D: My boss, and other owners of small construction businesses like the one I work in. And maybe Elon Musk because he's hugely improving cars and rockets.

De: But he's a jerk. And probably his real reason for going to Mars is to evade taxes.

P: So was Bill Gates in his early years. Being a jerk, I mean. But here we're just talking about whether they've done things that strengthen the economy.

De: I think Oprah Winfrey deserves her wealth. And Stephen Colbert 'cause he makes me laugh about the craziness in politics.

D: They're all in the political up, along with us voters.

P: It's hard to judge which individuals are in what you call the political up versus down. It's easier to do with businesses.

De: With individuals we just need to look at how much they give to politicians.

P: Following the flow of money in politics is like slicing an onion. There are lots of layers to cut through, and it becomes hard to see because tears come to your eyes. It's easier to separate the takers from the makers in businesses. We look at what the biz does.

D: What if the biz does both? Making and taking?

P: We can prorate it.

D: Get professionals to rate the business?

De: Prorating. It's another kind of division. It involves percentages.

D: Ah, got it. But my brain's startin' to drain 'cause this seems like sorting peaches from apricots. Is there some pattern? I mean for sorting takers from makers?

P: In general the spectrum from makers to takers would be something like this. It starts with farming and ranching. Then to manufacturing, cooking, brewing, entertaining, engineering, inventing, software developing, oil refining, research if it isn't market research, and other such making activities. Then to teaching and training. Then to healthcare, grocery sales, meat packing, canning, and maintenance. Then to shipping, retail stores, hospitality, and more. Then to advertising and marketing. Then finally to banking, insurance, legal services, real estate developers, logging, mining, casinos, alcohol businesses, and the tobacco industry.

De: I love it! Especially because sleazy real estate developers would be at the bottom paying the highest tax rates. Now it's finally so much clearer who I should fight! And how I can fight!

D: So you're saying that better voting methods would allow us voters to elect politicians who'd pass laws that change business taxes? In ways that would lead to a stronger economy? So there's a big flow of money into the United States?

De: And less profits for businesses that mostly earn their money from customers inside the U.S.? Like Wall Street and insurance companies?

P: I'm not saying what should be done, or will be done. I'm saying that economic prosperity would increase if those changes were made.

D: 'N it would only decrease prosperity for a few people who earn their money by owning taker businesses? That sounds great!

De: I'm ready for this fight!

D: Hey! I see a pattern. The owners of taker businesses are in the political down, 'n currently their businesses get so many tax breaks they pay low tax rates. 'N the owners of maker businesses, like the one I work in, 'n the one I'd like to build, they're in the political up. Yet they pay high tax rates, 'n get few tax breaks. We're taxin' the fruitful makers more than the vulture takers! The economy's like a bat takin' a nap. It's upside down!

De: Yes! The economic world is so very upside down! It's time to turn the economy right side up!

P: Alas, yes, the economic world is upside down.

De: I see something else! Suppose Wall Street businesses and law offices were taxed more. Their employees would earn less than they do now. So some smart employees on Wall Street and some smart lawyers would move from those taker businesses to maker businesses. Because those businesses would be taxed less. So they could pay better than now. That job migration would increase U.S. prosperity.

D: I see. They'd be less attracted to soul-sucking jobs on Wall Street. But wait a minute. ... I think that might mean a lower salary for me 'cause I'm not a smart guy.

P: Does this guy really not know how smart he is?

De: He hasn't done much reading so he's not book smart. But he's very smart in common sense. Which is all too uncommon, alas.

D: If I'm so smart, why'd I flunk out of community college?

De: Because you've got a reading disability that schools don't test for. That makes schools stupid. Not you.

D: My world's so upside down. In so many ways.

P: Let's fix that. What's still confusing?

D: I still don't know why so many people say it's easy to earn lots of money just by workin' extra hard.

P: That was true back in the nineteen fifties, sixties, and into the seventies.

D: What changed?

P: Remember that a big part of World War Two, in the nineteen fourties, was the bombing of factories and power plants. That destroyed lots of the efficiency that had been built in industrial nations.

D: Huh?

P: Here's a question. Which nations did not get their factories destroyed by bombs?

D: The United States.

De: And Canada.

P: That gave the United States and Canada a monopoly. A huge monopoly. What was it?

D: Factories! Manufacturing! The entire world had to buy manufactured goods from the U.S. and Canada.

P: Right. So what's that mean?

De: Huge amounts of money, to buy those goods, flowed into North America.

D: 'N that monopoly ended when other nations built new factories to replace the ones that were bombed.

P: A plus again! That's why U.S. economic prosperity peaked in the fifties and sixties. That's when the idea arose, well resurfaced, that anyone could get rich by working hard.

D: So it's like when there's a strong enough updraft, even slugs can fly?

De: Be careful where you're standing when that updraft ends.

P: That's the basic idea.

De: So during the fifties and sixties the middle class was bigger. That fits with what I've heard. Now that the middle class has shrunk, working hard to earn wealth is just bunk?

P: There's something called the Gini coefficient that measures income inequity.

D: It measures wickedness? I love it.

De: You're thinking of iniquity. This is inequity. As in inequality.

P: The Gini coefficient started rising in the late nineteen seventies. That's when getting to the middle class became harder.

D: That's when primary elections became common! 'N that's when more rich Republicans infiltrated Democratic primaries.

De: That's not just a coincidence is it?

P: Now you're getting to something I don't know.

D: So rising to the middle class based on hard work is something from the past?

P: I'm not a political scientist, yet I can see there's lots and lots of corruption in the U.S. And it's been increasing. But please appreciate that most other nations are even more corrupt. And never forget that corruption was worse in the past.

De: I need some optimism. Is there any hope that the big problems we face can be solved? Like global climate change?

P: Back when horses pulled wagons, big cities faced a big environmental dilemma. They predicted that soon cities would be knee high in horse shit. Yet that didn't happen. Not one bit.

D: They failed to predict automobiles would take over.

De: So our current climate crisis is like being ankle-deep in horse shit? Except it's invisible? This is optimistic?

D: What predictions are we failing to see? What solutions can solve our huge crises?

P: Perhaps the biggest overlooked solution is pairwise vote counting. You already know that will fix lots of bad feedback loops. And that will increase economic prosperity. Yet I've also read about some other promising solutions.

D: What are those?

P: I've read about fully synthetic hydrocarbon fuel, thorium nuclear reactors, new programming languages that will simplify automating things online, a fully phonetic writing system that will reduce illiteracy, open patents as an aternative to monopoly patents, dishwasher-sized kitchen appliances that will do food prep using robotics controlled by workers in distant countries, and a years-in-prison movie and game rating that will reduce crime. Plus I've got some personal guesses. There will be better micropayment systems that help individual entrepreneurs. And there'll be higher taxes on businesses that have more salary inequity between executives and workers.

D: Wow! It makes my gutter cleaning tool seem smaller than a bikini on a beach in Rio.

De: How do you know about these things?

P: I read. It's a form of time travel.

De: I read too, but this is all news to me.

P: I mostly read non-fiction. I skip over articles that are judgements, such as who's to blame, or what should be done, or what celebrities are promoting. Instead I like to read about why things are the way they are, which includes lots of history. And when there's a claim for a solution, I just focus on its advantages and disadvantages.

D: So what's blocking those future solutions from happening?

De: Let me guess. Feedback loops are keeping those things from getting developed.

P: A plus again!

D: So there's lots of feedback loops blocking progress. What's the feedback loop that blocks us from election reform?

P: There are many. As you've discovered, vote splitting is just one part of a feedback loop that keeps owners of many big businesses in political power. And they oppose solutions such as fully synthetic hydrocarbon fuel.

De: What's synthetic whatever?

P: Fully synthetic hydrocarbon fuel refers to gases and liquids that are chemically manufactured. The process would use sunlight as the energy source. It would get carbon from carbon dioxide in the atmosphere ...

De: Which we have too much of.

P: ... and it would get hydrogen from water.

D: So doing what plants do?

P: Yes, but much more efficiently. Especially compared to using crops to generate ethanol, which involves a few wealthy people who have a monopoly on ethanol.

D: If synthetic hydro ...

P: Fully synthetic hydrocarbon fuel

D: ... is such a good thing, what's blocking that from happening?

P: There's no economic incentive. The people who have the skills to figure it out cannot get paid to do that research.

D: Ah, another feedback loop.

De: Instead it's the lack of a feedback loop.

D: Is there something from history that would reveal how to make good changes happen sooner?

P: When Kodak tried to develop, so to speak, color film for cameras, their research labs were only making slow progress. But two young chemistry graduates were making better progress, so Kodak hired them.

D: What was the secret that gave them an advantage?

P: They were singers.

De: The secret was singing?

P: At that time color darkrooms were completely dark, so there was no way to see a timer. Yet the chemistry was very time-critical. So they sang songs together and used the timing of songs as their timer for chemical reactions.

De: So you're saying we need to take up singing?

P: It illustrates that breakthroughs often require sub-breakthroughs.

D: So this means we need to figure out some kind of innovation that will help spread the bigger innovation of fairer voting methods?

P: Yes. Look for a way to break the feedback loops that block fairer voting. Drill a hole through the dam that holds back the flood of fairness and economic prosperity that civilization is waiting for. Then voters can elect leaders who will be their puppets. Until then politicians are the puppets of the biggest campaign contributors. And typically they earn their money in ways that've become obsolete.

D: Any more tips?

P: One way to fight against bad feedback loops is to create opposing good feedback loops. Especially ones that increase economic prosperity.

D: I need an example again.

P: Democracy itself is a feedback loop. It yields far better economic prosperity compared to monarchy and dictatorship. That makes oppressed people jealous. That jealousy brought down the Berlin wall, toppled the dictators in eastern Europe, and ended the Cold War against the Soviet Union.

De: Wow! Jealousy isn't always a bad thing.

D: Feedback loops are not always bad?

P: Good and bad are just shortcut ways to say something has lots of advantages or lots of disadvantages. But it depends on who you are as to whether a change is an advantage or disadvantage. A feedback loop that helps big businesses get richer is good for the people who own that biz, but bad for their customers.

D: Ah, this is the cherry pie slicing concept.

P: And a feedback loop can be both good and bad for the same person. Like when a shareholder increases his share value because the business avoids giving pay raises to their employees and raises prices to their customers. But then those employees and customers can't afford to boost the price of the shares that shareholder wants to sell.

De: Ah, that's bad for shareholders when they want to cash in their shares. 'N yet good for shareholders 'cause those shares are worth more because worker salaries are lower and prices are higher.

D: Wow, so many feedback loops.

De: Your insights are amazing.

D: But my head is full!

P: To help you see how it all fits together, here's a thought. Voting, and taxes, and subsidies, and legal monopolies, and even jail time, are all forms of communication.

D: I can see that voters try to use their ballot to say we want more of this, and less of that. Alas, it's still at the mumbling stage of communication. But taxes, how is that communication?

De: I see! It's a way government can use lower taxes to say let's have more farming, more stockpiled emergency supplies, and more international sales of smartphone apps that do stupidly fun activities. Higher taxes say we need fewer pirates on Wall Street, and fewer businesses that overpay executives while underpaying workers. And Wall Street executives never going to jail gives the thumbs up to financial corruption.

D: Ah, that makes sense. Now hopefully I can better figure out how to earn money as an entrepreneur.

P: To do that you need to understand an important business concept. So here's a test. You'll probably fail, yet it'll exercise your brain. What do these people have in common? Steve Jobs, Bill Gates, Elon Musk, Thomas Edison, George Westinghouse, and Giovanni Marconi.

D: They are, or were, rich entrepreneurs.

P: And what else?

D: They got rich through tech. Technology.

P: And what else?

D: That's all my brain can guess.

De: This isn't something I ever learned.

P: They profited from technology that was created by creative geniuses.

D: Ah yes. Steve Jobs co-founded Apple with another guy.

P: Steve Wozniak, who designed and built the circuit board for what could have been called the Apple One. And Apple hired Jony Ive who is a design genius.

D: Bill Gates co-founded Microsoft with another guy.

P: Yes, Paul Allen. They bought code and renamed it Microsoft DOS, so there were creators behind that product. Later there were more creative geniuses behind Microsoft Windows.

D: Elon Musk has hired lots and lots of really smart engineers and software coders.

P: And now the trick part of the question. Who are the creative geniuses who created amazing technology breakthroughs for Thomas Edison, and George Westinghouse, and Giovanni Marconi?

D: I only know one of those. Nikola Tesla. He helped Westinghouse with electrical power stuff.

D: Indeed, he almost single-handedly designed our power grid system. Yet Tesla also invented key parts of radio technology that Marconi commercialized. And Tesla also did some inventing for Thomas Edison.

D: So why doesn't history teach more about people like Tesla?

P: Who's got the money it takes to erect statues, pay ghost writers to write autobiographies, and put into storage for future historians the person's voice recordings, and scribbled notes on napkins.

D: The people who win economically.

De: The creative geniuses who do the work get left out. Both from profits and historical recognition.

P: That's why I said the important part of history is understanding cause and effect. And now do you see what you should know about entrepreneurs?

D: Alongside, or behind, ... or underneath entrepreneurs, are the creative geniuses who create things of value that entrepreneurs sell.

P: Yes! And after creating the innovation that starts the business, those creators need to create yet more innovations. That keeps the business ahead of copycat businesses.

D: Is this like Walt Disney? He created lots of innovations.

P: Excellent example. In his case his brother Roy handled the money biz. So having a source of great ideas that become innovations can be a monopoly. Especially if competing businesses don't have creative geniuses working for them.

D: Ah, the ethical kind of monopoly.

De: Maybe now you can figure out how you can make money from your invention. Maybe by teaming up with an entrepreneur. You would be the creative genius.

D: If I could get a patent.

P: It takes lots of money to protect a patent.

D: I thought getting a patent was the hard part.

P: That's just a start. If it's a valuable idea then other businesses will infringe on your patent. So you have to take them to court to protect your monopoly. And China mostly ignores patents.

D: That sucks. Is there a way to ..., I don't know, to win in the business world?

P: The open patent I mentioned would help.

D: How does that work?

P: If it existed you could afford to register your idea with the patent office without mortgaging your house to pay for a patent attorney. You'd get a patent number. You'd add it to your LinkedIn profile. Then corporations would compete to hire you to invent yet more.

De: At a big salary!

D: That path doesn't yet exist. So what should I do?

D: Currently corporations don't know how to hire, or even recognize, creative geniuses. Not until after they've been the co-founder of a wildly successful start up.

D: That's a huge wall to climb.

P: Yes, alas. Under current conditions only hindsight reveals who's a creative genius. When that inefficiency gets solved, that will increase economic prosperity so dramatically that it will change the economy from a roller coaster ride into a rocket ship blasting into outer space.

D: Aren't most people creative?

P: It's like with art. Thousands of painters have painted portraits in very creative styles. But the Mona Lisa stands out as a style that's not just different. It's also widely appreciated by lots of people.

D: Ah, that's why you use the word genius after the word creative?

P: Yes, and to clarify that value of a product or a person becomes clear only in hindsight.

De: So solutions are waiting for less stupidity in politics. That's such a tiny light at the end of a long long tunnel. Is there any hope? For a fairer economy?

P: Look at history. Civilization has increased efficiency so much that us average folks don't waste big parts of our day hauling water, gathering firewood, tending horses, and pounding underwear against rocks. Now we waste too much time sitting in cars, working in the kitchen, and watching ads for extra-special soap. [fix_humor] Those time wasters and other inefficiencies in the economy will disappear after we adopt better laws. But that requires better vote-counting methods.

De: I'm discouraged by the setbacks. The ones going on now in politics.

P: In the past there've been huge setbacks too. Much bigger ones. The ancient Greeks two thousand years ago made clock-like computers that predicted eclipses. One of those was found in a shipwreck off the island of Antikythera.

D: Who was the creative genius behind that?

P: Probably either Posidonius or Hipparchus. Sadly, warfare killed their knowledge. Those kinds of mechanisms weren't developed again until the Islamic Golden Age. In a similar way, the footsteps on the moon might remain unmatched for decades.

De: That's so sad.

P: Yet when times get rough, more people say We've had enough! and they work together to make things better. That's where you two are.

D: Is there time?

P: Solutions are waiting. World war three is widely known to be a very stupid idea, for self-interest reasons. So there's time to get pairwise vote counting adopted in elections. And doing that should be easier than what early North American colonists had to do to get democracy. They had to fight with physical weapons. And they got lucky 'cause France and Spain and the Dutch all fought against England at that same time. Now the fights occur in cyberspace and in the news. Those fights don't risk your life. And they're winnable.

De: I think I see some light ahead. You've shown us a path to better times. I guess we just need to fight against some feedback loops. The ones that say we should jump for joy when a house burns down.

D: Now I see hope for creating ways to earn more money by making things of value. But now my head's so full it feels ready to become a fireworks display.

De: Professor Pengaritihas we're so grateful you've given us so much wisdom.

P: Ah, if only more people were anxious to learn like you two are.

D: What a pleasure! So how can we repay you?

P: Make the world a better place for my grandchildren. And get it right! Less corruption would help nearly everyone. And the few who lose will still have their huge bank accounts, so they and their families won't suffer. And then it will spread to other countries around the world where suffering is even worse. And that will help the children of my nieces and nephews. They live in India. In advance thank you for helping their offspring and mine.

De: We will fight to turn the world rightside up.

D: Yes, we'll do our best to turn the worlds of politics and economics and business rightside up.

De: This was well worth the four-hour drive to come meet with you.

P: Good luck! You'll need it. And remember that you didn't learn any of this from me.

De: We know how this works, so we promise!

D: Thanks for the master class in restoring the middle class. And Desha, let's talk this stuff over on the ride back home, shall we? So we can remember it.

De: Of course! What else would we want to talk about?

Scene 7, Fight!

J (Jordon): Father, I've given lots of money to your worthy church. I've asked you here because now I search for a way to buy the delay of death. Please give me a reprieve on my last breath.

W (Whit): The spiritual world soars above the physical world that your body is a part of. It's a pyramid. So the peak must rest on a solid foundation that cannot be weak. In other words, the golden rule of doing good deeds must rest on a foundation of not doing bad deeds.

J: No more Go Fudge Yourself ice cream? That's what you're sayin'? I promise I'll do better. So please do some prayin'!

W: It's not just what I say and what your brain thinks. It's what you do. It's your actions, your behaviors, that's what God listens to.

J: This heart attack has me scared. I fear death 'cause I'm not prepared.

W: To cast out fear, fill your heart with love. That's what your heart needs lots more of.

J: I have no kids and no real friends. I do love Benjamins, but that's where it ends. My money brings pleasure, and envy from others, and attracts gold diggers but not real lovers. Who can I love? How does that feel? Is there time to love? Can it really heal?

W: To love, first you must let go of darkness. Start with understanding that money is not evil. It's greed that is evil.

J: Is it greedy to want to have it all?

W: We are human, so all of us want it all. But there's not enough time or energy to acquire it all.

J: But there are shortcuts.

W: Most shortcuts increase suffering for others. That blocks you from rising spiritually, far above criminals and lawyers, I mean sinners. That's why the Bible says it's easier for a camel to fit through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to become a loving saint on earth. In other words, those shortcuts branch off the path that leads to the deepest kinds of love.

J: I do want to be loved. Yet I'm not yet tired of being admired.

W: Which has a higher priority?

J: It's all important.

W: For something to be important, everything else must be less important.

J: It's now important that I live. I now believe religion can give me more than what I had before my heart attack.

W: Do you embrace religion to do good deeds? Or just to feel less guilt for doing deeds that God would frown on?

J: I'm a bit lost. I'm in a fog. Don't I need to always fight to protect myself against the wicked evil in other people?

W: People are not inherently wicked. Wickedness fills books and movies. But that's fiction. Reality TV and kid's soccer games have to artificially inject scarcity because otherwise participants cooperate. And that's as boring as watching a homeless person snoring.

J: What about the news?

W: News sources make their money by selling your eyeballs and ears to advertisers. They attract our attention with stories that put a magnifying glass on the acts of audacious criminals, slimy politicians, and other morons.

J: What about the Holocaust?

W: During a time of nationwide starvation, and massive economic suffering, plus mass stupidity, the Nazi government gave permission to steal gold and cash and valuables from Jews. And consider that part of the reason Jews had become wealthy is that early Christians were taught they should not charge interest when lending dough. So they asked Jews living in ghettos to do the lending. That's why later it was so profitable for Germans to steal from Jews.

J: Surely there's no excuse for the evil in Nazi soldiers. And terrorists in the Middle East.

W: Soldiers and terrorists fight out of friendship for their comrades, not mainly for an ideology.

J: What if the ideology is money?

W: Yes, an opportunity to gain money or wealth can easily lead to evil deeds. Like when Japanese Americans were put into concentration camps partly as a way to steal the valuable southern California farmland that lots of Japanese Americans owned.

J: Is there an antidote? To evil?

W: Yes, talking. To people on the other side.

J: Talking. I do lots of that, as part of business.

W: Do you ask questions with a desire to understand the other person's point of view?

J: Why would I do that?

W: Consider what ended apartheid in South Africa. It was secret talks. One of them was between Nelson Mandela, and a clergyman, and the clergyman's twin brother who led a militant group that supported apartheid. Through talking, Mandela and the pro-apartheid leader discovered unexpected common ground.

J: Does this work in relationships? I admit I have lots to learn there.

W: Indeed. But don't expect you'll ever know what's in the other person's mind. Yet with practice you will find out that rarely is the other person evil, or stupid. And most of the time there is a path forward that benefits both sides.

J: My head is spinning. Without money as a compass I'm lost. And winning. That's the only goal I know.

W: Ah, yes, winning. Parents use winning prizes to entice kids to learn. But the real goal is the learning. With maturity we leave behind the gold stars, glitzy prizes, and eventually the winning. The skills we've learned remain, long after the trophies are lost. Now the skill you seek is spirituality. So it's time to let go of immaturity.

J: You're ripping away what's familiar. Can you give me a second compass? One that points up to higher goals? And a flashlight that points down to sharp rocks in my path ready to jab my ass?

W: Take in a deep breath. ... With each in-breath may we breathe in God's love, as represented by sunlight, and beautiful gardens, and spirited music, and joyful dancing, and especially laughter. ... With each out-breath may we exhale our dark fears, and dark anger, and our selfish desire for the very closest parking spot. Fling that darkness into the sun knowing it will be atomized and converted into light. ... When we let go of darkness we can better focus on beloved family members and friends. Even if dead, they still reside in our awareness.

J: Ah, the angry voices in my head. I'm happy to give them eviction notices. Sadly, I've got no friends in spite of my great wealth. Women say they want me. But they want unemployment and spending my money on countless shoes, dresses they wear only once, and trips to the mall to buy cosmetics that signal don't touch me. My world is upside down. Got no friends. Who can I trust?

W: Live in the present. Let go of the past. Not the memories. Just emotions like expired anger, out-of-date sadness, and the regret that you didn't choose the right words when you last saw someone alive. ... Let go of the future. Hold on to wise plans and wise goals. But let go of emotions like excess anxiety, the compulsion to pinch pennies, and the phobia of behaving like a four-eyed, five-star dork. [check_humor] They are feelings about our future, which isn't here yet. ... Now, the present, is where joy resides. Appreciate what you've already got. Appreciate wherever you already are. Appreciate whatever you are already doing. Wallow in the joy. And especially welcome it when it enters your life.

G (Grafton): [Knock on door.] ... Hello my friend! I brought you some beautiful flowers to brighten your spirits.

J: Ah, Grafton indeed welcome. And thank you for spending the, er, for thinking to bring flowers. ... They are beautiful.

G: I see you have recruited a minister to be part of your cure.

J: Allow me to introduce father, er, actually I now realize I don't know your name.

W: My name ....

J: Everyone calls him father. It's OK if he calls you father?

W: Of course.

G: Hello father. And Jordon, I look forward to your recovery so we can resume our latest project.

J: Let's not talk shop just right now. I need to focus on breathing in the joy of still being alive. Stressful things can come later, if I survive.

W: What other protective perspectives can I offer?

J: How can God be everywhere? How can I be sure that God even cares about me?

W: Try thinking of God as being like the principles of mathematics.

J: Elusive? How is that helpful?

W: If you live your life as if two plus two equals thirteen then life becomes hell. But if instead you live your life as if two plus two equals four, then life becomes joyful. That's how God is everywhere. Just as the principles of mathematics are everywhere.

J: I like that outlook. Why have I not heard you say it from your perch, your pulpit in church?

W: There are some things we can't preach.

J: Like what?

W: If we speak out with boldness against war, that would impair our tax-exempt status.

G: That's right! Churches don't pay property taxes. Maybe I should form a church to get that sweet deal.

J: What else can you not say in church?

W: Many ministers manipulate their flock by transforming guilt into shame. But the best ministers transform guilt into choosing actions that don't lead to new guilt. That shifts the focus from resisting sin, to adopting high standards of ethical behavior. But attendance would suffer even more if we preached at that higher spiritual level.

K (Katerina): [Door opens and closes.] ... Father! I couldn't wait any longer in the waiting area. There's an awful nasty woman, with wild hair, who was harassing me.

G: Jordon, and father, allow me to introduce my daughter, Katerina.

J: It's a pleasure to have your company.

W: Pleased to meet you. [Click of keys as Whit types text message.]

G: This is my friend Jordon.

K: It's a pleasure to meet you both. I'm sorry to interrupt. Please resume whatever you were talking about.

J: Father, why in church do you not talk more about what you've said here? Instead you refer so much to the names and words in the Bible.

W: Our hands are tied. Especially we can't conflict with politics.

J: Ah, so you can't criticize politicians who lack morality.

W: We each do the best we can within our limitations.

De (Desha): [Door opens and closes.] ... Father what did you mean by texting the words Causing trouble again?

K: She's the one! She's the nasty, perverse, foul-mouthed bitch who yelled at me.

W: Did you curse?

De: Quite the reverse. She threw some trash toward the trash can and it missed, but she didn't pick it up. I spoke up.

K: As I told you then, this hospital has janitors whose job it is to pick up pieces of trash. Speaking of which, maybe I should have tossed you in with the other trash.

W: May I request that you give less stress to Jordon while he gets rest after his heart attack?

De: I apologize for the stress.

K: Of course I apologize.

J: I have to admit this is better than Netflix or TV. So it's not bothering me.

K: In that case I'll say you're a witch for attacking me.

De: I was attacking stupidity. If you're pleading guilty it's a case of double stupidity.

W: Even if Jordon doesn't mind, let's have serenity and sanity shall we?

K: I'll text Damien. He can take me home so I won't trouble you further father, or you father, or you Jordon. [Click of keys as Katerina types text message.]

W: Desha do you remember Jordon?

De: Yes, I think I do, although it's been a long time.

J: Indeed. What have you been up to?

De: I've been working for politicians, and environmental organizations.

G: I'll bet you're one of those awful protesters who are protesting against my latest development project.

De: So you're the ... grrr, ... developer behind the deaths of so many wild animals and the cutting of beautiful trees on that Smoldering Ashes property?

G: It's called Slumbering Maples. Yes I am.

De: If ever there was a time I'd like to swear this is it!

G: Perhaps this isn't a great time to bring it up, but I have not understood why religion deserves exemption from taxes. Especially since religion seems so, well, antiquated.

W: Desha has some thoughts on this.

De: Since before the Roman empire, churches have brought beautiful music to the ears of people who were not rich enough to hire musicians. Now, anyone with a bulge in their pocket can listen to any song at any moment. So churches lost that advantage. First to phonographs, then to radios, and now smartphones.

W: Alas, competing sources of beautiful music partly accounts for our congregations being small. Fortunately people who love to sing together are still attracted.

De: And long ago marriage in a church was a way for a young woman to trade sex in exchange for getting her husband to attend church and hear sermons about doing good.

G: I must admit my wife has wanted me to attend church with her.

De: Then governments copied that idea and now marriage is done as a civil ceremony. Plus courts and the IRS force child support and alimony payments from men who abandon their children or their wives.

W: Yes, marriage ceremonies. That was a big monopoly churches had, then lost.

K: And churches used to feed the hungry. Now that's done with food stamps from the government. So that's one more advantage lost?

W: Yes.

De: Universities and schools were founded alongside churches and mosques. Now, governments fund those too.

J: So government is taking over increasing morality?

W: Only some of it! We still serve a very useful service of reminding folks to act in ways that are fair and benevolent. But religion is about much more than just ending bad behavior. That's just the beginning of the spiritual world.

K: A few badly behaving priests in the Catholic Church need to learn from your wisdom.

W: Alas, with low attendance, there are fewer funds, so churches can't be as picky about choosing ministers. And those of us with the highest ethics don't get paid much more than beginners.

K: And the clergy sinners.

De: Recently I learned about a way that crime can be reduced without churches being involved.

W: Good golly bonnie lass!

K: Movies and games can get another rating. The added rating would indicate how many years a person would spend in prison if they did everything shown on the screen.

J: [Laughs.]

K: [Laughs.]

W: [Laughs.]

G: Harrumph! That won't work.

De: What won't work is the version in your head. But that's not the version that my words are intended to mean.

D (Damien): [Door opens and closes.] [He now uses better, but not perfect, pronunciation.] Hello!

K: Sweetheart, I need you to give me a ride home because this nasty woman is being obnoxious to me.

D: Hi Desha.

K: You know this bitch?

D: She's the woman I've told you about.

K: You said that woman was like a kid sister to you. But she's looking at you with love in her eyes.

D: Don't be ridiculous. She's got a boyfriend.

De: I do not.

D: Then who's the guy named Willie? The guy you said you're with.

De: Willie is short for Willamina. That's an awful name to get stuck with.

D: You said he, er, she, is your partner. So are you, well, lesbians?

De: We're both bisexual.

J: Much much better than Netflix.

K: You keep your claws off of him! Damien, you are never to see her again!

D: Well, ah, I can't promise anything.

G: You're engaged to my daughter so I too forbid you to ever see this awful woman again.

D: She's helping me to figure out how I can earn more money to make your daughter happy.

De: I thought you were trying to figure out how to reduce corruption in the political world.

D: They're both the same thing to me. I figured out how corruption works, so now I'm tryin' to figure how to work around it. Then I can start my own business. I'll be the employer, not the employee.

K: You've told me some of what you've learned, but you haven't yet said who's to blame for corruption.

D: I'm the one to blame. It's not politicians, not the big campaign contributors, not the lobbyists 'n other folks who are hired to do political tasks. I'm the one to blame.

K: How can you be the one to blame? You haven't done anything.

D: Exactly. I failed. I failed to subtract forty from one hundred 'n realize the result, sixty, is more than fifty.

K: You said math was made by the devil. When he was in a snit. And now you're talking math? This doesn't fit. Not one bit.

D: My fear of math was blocking me. Now I know that a candidate who gets forty percent support is opposed by sixty percent of voters. That's a majority. That means the majority of voters oppose a candidate who has less than fifty percent support. To get fair election results we need ranked ballots 'n pairwise counting.

G: What does counting smart rabbits have to do with voting?

K: Father it's not wise hare counting. It's pairwise counting.

D: Without that change corruption in Congress will continue.

De: When a news report says one candidate leads another by say five percent, that's meaningless, unless there are just two candidates on the ballot.

J: Hello Damien.

D: Oh hi Jordon. I didn't recognize you with the tubing mustache. Is this a good time to thank you for helping me figure out how the world of business works?

J: I was happy to help. Grafton said you deserved some help.

G: What did you say to this ungrateful young man?

J: As you requested I told him how the world of business works. He had some questions about money in politics that I couldn't answer so I referred him to a politician I know. How did that go?

D: He taught me a lot. Then later, he suggested that Desha and I meet and collaborate.

J: What was his great wisdom? In a nutshell.

D: He explained that vote splitting's why money has more influence than votes.

G: Goats do not spit. You fool.

K: Father, it's not goat spitting, it's vote splitting.

G: Whatever! Votes are counted in ways that are fair. So that's got not a thing to do with money in politics.

De: I used to think that too.

D: When you donate money to political candidates, sometimes you give to Democrats. Am I right?

G: Never! I always vote Republican. And I never give money to Democrats.

K: But mother is a Democrat, and sometimes you give her money to donate to a Democratic candidate.

G: That's only when my political consultant tells me to.

D: So when Barack Obama and Hillary Clinton ...

G: Those are vile names to me and my friends. Isn't that right Jordon?

J: Let him continue. This is interesting.

D: Some political strategists recommended that Republicans give money to Obama during the Democratic primary with the idea that a black man could not possibly win the general election. With that strategy they figured that a Republican would win easily.

G: You can't prove any of this. And without proof there's no crime.

D: The fight between political left and right is an entertaining distraction from the real, bigger fight between political up and political down.

G: You're talking more nonsense.

J: Who is the political up?

D: Most of us voters.

J: And who is the political down?

D: The people who give the biggest amounts of money to politicians.

De: That includes you, Grafton, and you Jordon.

W: Oh dear lord, my own daughter is undermining my church.

G: She's your daughter?

W: Indeed.

De: Why do you think I call him father?

J: We all call him father.

D: This explains why I don't hear her use profanity.

De: Father is very strick about that.

D: Since I'm not in your church, what should I call you?

W: You can call me Whit.

D: What?

W: Whit, it's short for Whittier.

K: Who are you wittier than?

W: It's spelled W H I T.

G: So in grade school they called you dimwit and half-wit?

W: At that age my nickname helped me learn to identify immaturity.

J: Damien, you were saying something about political up and political down.

D: Vote splitting's the reason that money still has so much influence in politics. In the early days of the U.S. there were no primary elections. Slowly voters 'n parties learned that whichever party had just one candidate would easily win over parties that had two or more candidates.

De: So primary elections were added to ensure each party offered just one candidate in what we now call general elections.

G: And the point is?

D: If we used ranked ballots and pairwise counting, then Democrats could have offered both Obama and Clinton as candidates in the two thousand eight presidential election.

J: Ah, so the tactic of using Obama to block Clinton wouldn't have been an option.

De: And wealthy folks like yourselves would not have been able to stop Clinton from winning.

G: This is all nonsense!

J: It's making sense to me.

G: Who's side are you on?

J: I am now on the side of God. My heart attack has woken me up to what's really important in life. And at the moment I want the truth to come out. If there are hidden parts of politics that get revealed here we can judge it at that time.

G: I suppose you're going to claim that Donald Trump won in twenty sixteen because of money. Well he didn't. I didn't give him even a dollar.

De: But you do give to the Republican party, and they paid to promote Trump after he won the primary.

D: If the twenty sixteen Republican primary election had used ranked ballots and pairwise counting, the winner would have been the most popular candidate, and that was not Donald Trump.

De: There were sixteen other candidates in that race. That split the votes of the majority of Republicans. They wanted someone other than Trump.

D: All Trump and his promoters, including Russian hackers, needed was to win more votes than any one of the other sixteen candidates.

De: None of whom were very popular.

D: Until the other candidates dropped out, Trump was getting less than half the votes. And that's just Republicans. He would have lost under a fairer election.

J: Who would have won?

D: We don't know because even the sample polls don't ask voters for more than their favorite.

G: But Trump won the general election, so that proves he was more popular than Hillary.

D: But with ranked ballots and pairwise counting there would have been at least one more Republican and at least one more Democrat to win against.

De: Plus Bernie Sanders running as an independent.

D: Trump could not have won such a five-way race.

J: So you're saying that if we used ranked ballots and pairwise counting then voters would have more choices on the ballot?

D: Even better than more choices, the choices would include wise problem-solving leaders. Now the only choices are special-interest puppets.

De: Under current conditions, wise and ethical leaders don't enter elections because they know they won't get support from party insiders, who have to cater to people like you, with lots of money.

J: These so-called wise leaders, would they be liberal or conservative?

De: Neither.

D: They would represent the political up, and would oppose the political down.

G: So they're anti-business.

D: They would favor fairness and economic efficiency, er, efficiency in the economy. That would bring prosperity much greater than what we have today.

G: Prosperity to who?

D: Widespread prosperity.

G: That's impossible! In order to have winners there must be losers.

De: That's what I used to think. But fighting wastes precious resources. What yields better results for the most people is cooperation, teamwork, and working together against a foe.

W: I like this shift.

J: Did you just curse?

K: Not everyone can afford to fly to London and Paris. I agree with father that for there to be winners there have to be losers.

D: You want to fly to London and Paris?

De: I've told you I enjoy traveling.

D: I thought you meant by car.

J: Back to the idea of no losers. Surely some folks would lose out economically if elections were more fair.

D: Yes, there are some businesses that exploit unfairness and they would have their profits reduced because of higher taxes. And because of fewer monopolies.

J: Such as?

D: Did you know we pay lots more for sugar compared to the rest of the world? On the commodity market there's sugar number eleven and sugar number, ... ah, ...

De: Sixteen.

D: The price within the U.S. is the higher price, and the lower price is what the rest of the world pays. The people who exploit that legal monopoly would lose income, although they would keep their current wealth.

G: I'll bet that us developers would lose out.

De: Indeed! Your business taxes would be increased. 'N you deserve that 'cause mostly what you do is buy land, then use sneaky election tactics to control city councils to change the designation of that land to higher-rent uses, and force taxpayers to pay for new infrastructure, then hire workers to build buildings, and then you rent or sell the buildings at inflated prices. And doing all that doesn't require brains, just immorality.

G: That's completely legal.

De: Yes because you control elected city councilors, and state legislators, and congressmen, who write the laws.

J: So tell me what I really want to know. Would taxes increase on the businesses I own?

D: Some would pay lower taxes, and others would pay higher taxes.

J: That's not specific.

De: Businesses that exploit would pay higher taxes.

D: Businesses that bring benefits would pay lower taxes.

J: That's still not specific.

De: Developers like you would pay higher taxes.

G: On what basis?

De: You do not bring a net gain to the local economy.

G: On the contrary! People from elsewhere would move here.

De: And that would bring money to you, but would increase traffic, and it would increase infrastructure costs to those of us already here.

D: Plus your business requires lots of regulation, which is a drain on city management budgets.

J: Tell me which kinds of businesses would get lower taxes.

D: The ones that bring money into the region from outside the region. That includes businesses that involve software, art, making things, manufacturing, entertainment, non-chain restaurants, and such.

J: They get lower taxes? Why?

De: Because they bring a net flow of money into the city and county.

J: You said non-chain restaurants. Why not chain restaurants?

D: They send lots of their profits to corporate headquarters, which drains money from the city and state where the restaurant's located.

G: My business hires lots of workers.

De: But only temporarily. After development the jobs are gone. The kinds of businesses that get lower taxes continue to employ people as long as they stay in business.

J: Ah, I think I'm beginning to see. Raise taxes on activities that drain the economy, and reduce taxes on activities that enrich the economy.

D: Exactly!

W: So it taxes the sinners and helps the saints?

De: That's a useful way to view it.

W: I like it! Even though it might offend many of the folks who need religion the most. Like lawyers, bankers, and CFOs.

D: Aliens?

De: Not UFOs. CFOs. Chief financial officers. Father takes seriously the saying know thine enemy.

W: Our church welcomes everyone. Yet we do promote good deeds and frown on exploitation.

De: So the different tax rates are like the difference between a résumé and a eulogy. A résumé values money, a eulogy values benefiting others.

J: Interesting distinction! What I've accomplished would look fabulous on a résumé. But now it's time to consider what might be said in my eulogy.

G: I don't see the difference. But then religion isn't my thing.

D: Lately, with the worlds of business and government declining in ethics, we the voters need to fight for fairness!

K: So is fairness or money more important to you?

D: Why can't we get both?

K: Getting to the point, do you want to earn more money so we can afford maybe a few luxuries in life?

D: I want to build a business that provides something that benefits the customers. My original plan was to manufacture my leaf gutter cleaning tool so that fewer people fall off ladders when cleaning their gutters. Yet lately, other inventions have been popping into my mind. Most are for the kitchen food prep appliance someone told us about.

G: Your mind is in the gutter. None of that makes sense.

J: Mmm, I'm beginning to see the value of creating that kind of business if it gets taxed less.

De: And fewer toes would get stepped on.

J: As a bachelor, a kitchen food prep machine sounds like maybe a good alternative to getting so much takeout delivered.

D: That sounds like a good fit. Yet another benefit of taxing takers more than makers is that very smart well-educated people would be less attracted to soul-sucking jobs in banks and law firms.

De: And real estate.

D: Instead they'd work where they benefit customers, and clients, and the overall economy.

De: Well said! And to the teaching profession, which could use the very best role models for students. That's what Willie does. She's a teacher.

G: So who's going to believe this nonsense that different ballots and different ways of counting votes is really going to make things better?

De: This situation is like when women demanded the right to vote. A few places, like Canada, Australia, and New Zealand, tried it. Then a few western states tried it. The predicted disasters didn't follow, so it was adopted throughout the United States. And don't you think it's made things better?

G: Sometimes I wonder. We don't seem to be doing that well now that women have taken over.

De: Without Rosie the riveters working in factories during the war years U.S. soldiers might have lost. And a woman in the White House couldn't possibly be worse than what we've got now.

G: So Damien, do you agree with her?

D: It makes sense to me sir.

G: So Katerina, do you still want this guy as your future husband?

K: So Damien, do you still want to work hard so we can enjoy a nice lifestyle?

D: Willin' to work hard, that I'm willin' to do. But how nice of a lifestyle do ya have in mind?

K: Just a cute three-bedroom house with a fireplace. And of course a big backyard for a dog. But it can be smaller than a Saint Bernard. And a comfortable car for road trips and errands. And sometimes a trip to London or Paris.

D: I thought our plan was to enjoy time at home eating healthy food, and relaxing on the weekend, plus spending time with friends.

K: Of course all of that too.

G: And of course your mother and I want grandchildren.

D: If the worlds of politics, and business, and the economy, were not so upside down, then all of that, plus a tiara, would be within our reach. But now we're living during a time of transition. I'm afraid we could enter a new dark age if we stay on the path we're on. Instead I want to help make the world a better place for everyone's grandkids, even if that means I, or we, have to make a few sacrifices.

K: Oh father, what should I do? This isn't the way I want things to be.

G: You are my precious princess so I'll continue to give you money if that's what it takes to keep you happy.

K: This puts me in an awkward place.

D: The fact that you have to think about which to choose tells me that it's me who should lose.

W: It's clear to me that you love one another, so don't have doubt about your love.

De: There are plenty of single jerks with lots of money. ... Jordon, I'm not including you.

J: No offence taken. And perhaps you're a bit right.

De: It's easy to find a guy who earns good money stepping on people's toes. But if he's young he'll pick you up in a pickup truck double parked, engine revving, and honking his horn. Young mature men are hard to find. So do you want money or maturity?

K: I want both.

D: Then it's clear that you value money more than you value who I really am. I'll clear out my things in a few days.

K: Can we still be friends?

D: Of course, provided I can also remain friends with Desha.

G: Since you won't become my son-in-law I won't insist on you not being friends with this ...

K: Skank. That's the word I think you want.

De: Father taught me long ago that when someone criticizes another it's as if they're pointing into a mirror. So the critic's the one who deserves their own criticism.

J: Father, Whit, you've raised a great daughter. Grafton, after I'm recovered we can talk more about our project. In the meantime, I hate awkward conversations, and misty eyes and tears that flow, so it's time for you, Grafton, and your daughter to go.

G: I promise that my development project will bring great things to this city and county. Come my princess, it's time to leave.

K: Until you can get all your stuff, I'll pack some clothes and such in a box, and I'll text you when it's in the hall.

D: Thanks. And remember I do love you.

K: I know. That's why I wanted to marry you.

G: Let's get out of this inhospitible hospital. Bye! [Door opens and closes.]

J: Normally I'd suggest lightening up the mood with some ice cream. But times have changed. So I'll just say that was the most entertaining drama I've seen since high school prom night. And I'll add that you two, Damien and Desha, seem like wonderful young people to me. And I've learned that I could use a few new friends. So if either or both of you want to come and visit me at home after I'm out of this place, you're invited.

De: I'm beginning to see that not all wealthy people are bad. But I've been told I'm a bad-ass, and that's not going to change. So unless you like being criticized for your money quest, staying away might be best.

D: As for me, probably I should call my mother and be a moocher for a bit.

De: If that gets old you can come and stay with Willie and me.

D: So is it true what Katerina said about seeing love for me in your eyes?

De: You are very smart, but sometimes you can be so dense.

D: I'm not tall. Or handsome. As you know I've got no money I can offer.

De: The reason Willie and I are single is that we don't tolerate jerks. And most guys are just that, jerks. But you're not. You have spirit, a sense of fairness, a willingness to work through rough times. And you've got a great ass.

D: Wouldn't your Willie be jealous?

De: We're willing to share.

J: That's something money can't buy!

W: I'm fond of her Willie, in case you wonder about someone you've not yet met.

J: I can be dense too. But even I know that this is when you two should kiss.

D: Whit, do I need your permission?

W: If you can tame this wild lass, then gladly I give you her ... hand.

D: I don't think she needs to be tamed. She just needs to continue fighting against corruption. And that's a fight I'm willing to share.

De: You really do care! [Desha moves to Damien, they kiss on the lips, then hug.]

J: Father, Whit, was just telling me I need more love in my life. You've brought your love here for me to appreciate. So go for it you wise and also stupid fools!

De: In so many ways, for far too long, the world has been upside down. Now it's time to fight for what's right. And turn the world rightside up!

J: If it would help me, or might inspire a better eulogy for me, then perhaps I can help make that happen. Let's discuss this some more at my lonely home.

De: Can my Willie come?

J: Of course! A party! And not the political kind. I'll pay for Chinese takeout.

De: Father knows a good place for Chinese takeout.

W: Oh yes, Foo Ken Good Palace. It's on southeast Assinhole Avenue.

J: [Chuckles.] Whit do you want to come too?

W: More sparks for the fireworks? I'll decline. Yet I'm all in favor of turning the world rightside up. After all, turning things rightside up is the purpose of religion.

D: Holy guacamole! I never realized that's religion's grand prize.

De: Of course some churches need to subtract out the corrupt bits for that description to fit.

J: I'm learning a lot today. Now I see that I mistook jealosy for love. People want a financial connection with me, but then they'd be happy to push me aside, or even wish me dead, to transfer some of my wealth to themselves. Alas, my world has been upside down. It's not the way I want things to be. I want love like everyone else. I too want to help begin to turn the world rightside up.

De: I see you have a good heart. Now you can make a wiser start.

D: Yes we'll visit you at your home. Surely there's a way to merge what we all want. Hopefully we can find a way to promote pairwise vote counting to turn the world rightside up!

De: Yes! And let's start by joining forces together! [They kiss again.]

W: I can see the sparks flying already.

J: I do enjoy fireworks.

De: So do I! [Desha reaches out and holds a hand with Jordon.] Speaking of which, ... Jordon, I won't stop kicking your ass. But in fairness you're welcome to try to kick mine.

J: You can try to step on my toes. Anything goes.

De: Deal! [Desha goes back to put arm behind Damien.]

D: Speaking of kicking ass, I still want to see your kick ass tatoo.

De: A private showing of her is in your future.

Acknowledgements

Cynthia S., Andrew W., Eduard H., George "Vonnegut" (a comedy writing genius), Mia Moore (another comedy writing genius), Matt Y., [...]

Resources: RhymeZone.com, Rhymer.com, TheFreeDictionary.com, Dashrep.org

Here's a special posthumous thank you to caregiver Lottie Klock who taught me joy by giving me unconditional love during infancy.

Voice Actor Casting Requirements

D: Damien, young adult male, tenor voice.  Slight Puerto Rican accent.  In earlier scenes uses slightly lazy pronounciation (such as lookin' instead of looking) on non-important words.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

K: Katerina, young adult female, soprano or alto voice.  Speaks as though raised in an upper middle-class family.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

J: Jordon, middle-age adult male, baritone voice.  Speaks boldly as if wealthy.   See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

F: Fred Finckster, older adult male, tenor voice.  Speaks like an experienced politician.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

De: Desha, young adult female, alto voice.  U.S. American accent, but voice sounds like racially she is mixed-race with some African-American ancestry in addition to European ancestry.  Speaks strong political opinions.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

M: Mata, middle-age female, soprano or alto voice.  Sounds like a university professor.  Clear enunciation is important.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

P: Pengaritihas, middle-age male, tenor voice.  Slight Indian accent, as if he is the son of immigrants from India.  (At least pronounces "the" as "thee" rather than "thuh".)  Sounds like a university professor.  Clear enunciation is important.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

W: Whit (pronounced like "wit"), middle-age male, tenor voice.  Voice sounds like he could be the father of Desha, who is of mixed-race with both African-American and European ancestry.  Sounds like a wise minister or clergyman.  Clear enunciation is important.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

G: Grafton, middle-age male, bass or baritone voice.  Sounds like a pompous wealthy person.  See below for voice requirements that apply to all characters.

Voice requirements for all characters:  The voices need to be natural (full-throated and conversational), lively (frequent pitch inflections and word-specific loudness changes, although never in the middle of a syllable), and smiling (comedic, but not "funny").  A good sense of rhythm, either as a singer or dancer, is desired.  When a word rhymes without being at the end of a sentence or phrase, use slight timing or emphasis adjustments to allow the rhyming to be heard at least subconsiously.  The voice acting must not be self-conscious, and must not involve shouting.  A directed session — either a phone call or Zoom call — initially may be needed, or else approval of samples is needed.  A professional-quality microphone and silent background is essential.  Delivery must be high-resolution WAV format.

Additional characteristics are revealed in the dialog.